jBC/jBASE Features

Case sensitive keywords and variable names.
Optional statement labels.
Code sections accessed by GOSUB.
IF...THEN..ELSE conditional statement.
BEGIN CASE...CASE...END CASE conditional statement.
FOR...NEXT loop.
DO..WHILE/UNTIL...REPEAT loop.
External subroutines and functions.
Weak variables typing; implicit types conversion.
Dimensioned and dynamic arrays.
String, number, and date data conversion.
Patterns matching.
Unary operators support.
Single- and multi-byte character sets support.
Bitwise operations.
Standard industry encryption algorithms support.
Named and unnamed COMMON areas.
Operations with SELECT lists.
File and record level locking capability; distributed lock system.
Text files processing.
Functions for XML processing.
Manipulations with environment variables.
Emulation modes for compatibility with numerous MV platforms.
Practically unlimited data file size (OS limits apply).
Data files distribution.
Transactions support.
Transparent access to jBASE data and dictionary files converted to Oracle, DB2 or MS SQL.
Possibility to call C or Java code.
Possibility to execute any jBASE, system or database enquiry command.
Source code editor - JED (also capable of editing data files).
Debugger.

Guidelines for Writing Source Code

Recommendations (not rules)

Note: some examples in this documentation don't fully follow these rules - they were taken from other sources or it's done intentionally to illustrate some language features.

All variables are to be in lower case and in the lower_case_and_underscore_naming style.

Use only one style of quotes for strings, e.g.: "QWERT" (double quotes, preferable) or 'QWERT' (single quotes). Mix them only if it's really required, e.g.:

CRT '"Yes Minister", ' : "that's what I said."

Always use one space after the comma and never before the comma.

Never use space after '(' and before ')' (exception is when code is more readable with it).

Never put multiple commands on a single line and separate them by ";", except for short similar statements, like:

var_1 = 1 ; var_2 = 2 ; var_3 = 3

Don't put trailing ';' at the end of the lines.

Never convert ints to boolean implicitly:

Instead of:

   IF INDEX(...) THEN

always write:

   IF INDEX(...) NE 0 THEN

Same goes for strings. Instead of:

   var = 'ABC'
   IF var THEN  ;* code continues here

Use:

   IF var NE '' THEN  ;* code continues here

Never hardcode program or subroutine name in error messages etc. Use SYSTEM(40) instead.

Always supply meaningful error messages with sufficient additional information.

Don't comment what you do; comment why.

Don't mix tabs with spaces, use either former or latter.

Don't use characters with ASCII code above 126 in the source. To form strings with such characters use CHAR() or load them from external file or table.

Use CR (ASCII 10) for line ends rather than CR+LF.

For statements like INCLUDE, $INSERT use zero indent; for all other code - 3 spaces of initial indent and 3 spaces to indent each FOR...NEXT, LOOP...REPEAT contents etc.

Wrap lines that are longer than 80 characters (use a backslash or comma at the end where the latter is applicable). It's a good idea to move line continuation(s) even more than 3 positions to the right, e.g.:

current_date = DATE() current_day = OCONV(current_date, 'DD') current_month = OCONV(current_date, 'DM') ansi_date = OCONV(current_date, 'DY') : '-'
: FMT(current_month, 'R0%2' ) : '-'
: FMT(current_day, 'R0%2' ) CRT ansi_date ;* e.g. 2013-03-08

Use spaces around "=": not "var=1" but "var = 1".

Use "=" for assignment only; for comparisons use "EQ".

Don't use IF..ELSE without THEN.

Avoid GOTO, RETURN TO as much as possible.

Use named COMMON rather than unnamed.

Don't use numeric line labels like:

001 A = 0 002 A += 1 003 IF A LT 5 THEN GOTO 002 ELSE CRT A

Avoid ambiguity with IF...AND...OR, use parentheses. In the following example code lines 2, 3 and 4 are the same (except parentheses); only second IF is true:

var_1 = 1 ; var_2 = 2 ; var_3 = 3 ; var_4 = 4 IF var_1 EQ 1 OR var_2 EQ 20 AND var_3 EQ 30 OR var_4 EQ 40 THEN CRT 1 IF var_1 EQ 1 OR (var_2 EQ 20 AND var_3 EQ 30 OR var_4 EQ 40) THEN CRT 2 IF (var_1 EQ 1 OR var_2 EQ 20) AND (var_3 EQ 30 OR var_4 EQ 40) THEN CRT 3

Use only one method of writing "not equal" (preferably "NE").

(See the second example in chapter "Other notes".)

@USER.ROOT, @USER.THREAD and @USERSTATS

The use of the @USER.ROOT command allows a jBC program to store and retrieve a string of up to 63 bytes that is unique to that user. The intention is to really "publish" information that other programs can find.

For example:

   @USER.ROOT = "Temenos T24 Financials"
   .....
   PRINT "root user declaration is" : @USER.ROOT

See attribute <28>, USER_PROC_USER_ROOT, in the section "Layout of user record"

The @USER.THREAD is similar except a value exists for each PERFORM level. So one program can set/retrieve it but if the program does a PERFORM of a second program then the second program gets a different set of values.

See attribute <52>, USER_PROC_USER_THREAD, in the section "Layout of user record"

The @USERSTATS allows a program to retrieve all sorts of miscellanous information about itself. For example if a program wants to find out how many database I/O's it performed it could do this:

INCLUDE JBC.h
   info1 = @USERSTATS
   read1 = info1<USER_PROC_STATS_READ>
   EXECUTE 'COUNT fb1 WITH *A1 EQ "x"'
   info2 = @USERSTATS
   read2 = info2<USER_PROC_STATS_READ>
   PRINT "The COUNT command took " : (read2-read1) : " READs from the database"

So a program can set a user-definable string to whatever value it likes, up to 63 bytes, and other programs can use various methods (see "User Information Retrieval" below) to access this data.

User Information Retrieval

There are 3 ways of finding information about one or more users on a TAFC system:

Using the @USER.ROOT, @USER.THREAD and @USERSTATS variables in your jBC code you can find information about yourself. You cannot find information about other users.

The "WHERE (V" command can be used to display the @USER.ROOT and @USER.THREAD data for specified users.

Using some jBC code you can find out lots of information about each user on the system. This is exactly the mechanism that the WHERE command uses. For example to display all users logged on you could write this.

Example:

INCLUDE JBC.h
   * Open the special jEDI file to access the user information.
   OPEN SYSTEM(1027) TO PROC ELSE STOP 201,SYSTEM(1027)
   SELECT PROC
   * For each user logged on read in their user information
   LOOP WHILE READNEXT key DO
       READ rec FROM PROC, key THEN
          PRINT "Port " : rec<USER_PROC_PORT_NUMBER> :   \
             " is logged on by user " : rec<USER_PROC_ACCOUNT>
      END
   REPEAT

Layout of user record

The information retrieved by either the READ in the above example or the @USERSTATS is the same and is as follows.

The first 40 attributes are data attributes that correlate to the entire user. Attributes 41 onwards are multi-valued and have one value per program being PERFORM'ed by that user

All the numbers below can be replaced by symbolic references in JBC.h, look for those that begin from "USER_PROC_".

<1> The port number

<2> The number of programs running in this port.

<3> Time the user started in Universal Co-ordinated Time or UTC (not a dyslexic mistake). This is raw UNIX time. You can convert this to TAFC internal time format using the U0FF0 conversion or to internal date format using the U0FF1 conversion.

<4> The process ID

<5> Account name

<6> User name. Normally the operating system name.

<7> Terminal name in TAFC format

<8> Terminal name in Operating system format.

<9> Database name

<10> TTY device name

<11> Language name.

<12> Time in UTC the listening thread last found the thread alive.

<13> Amount of heap space memory in free space chain on a process wide basis. Not real-time, only updated every 15 seconds.

<14> Amount of heap space memory in use on a process wide basis. Not real-time , only updated every 15 seconds

<15> Thread type as an internal integer.

<16> Type of thread as a text string.

<17> License counters

<18> Number of OPENs performed.

<19> Number of READs performed.

<20> Number of WRITE's performed.

<21> Number of DELETE's performed

<22> Number of CLEARFILE's performed

<23> Number of PERFORM/EXECUTE's performed.

<24> Number of INPUT's performed.

<25> Not used.

<26> Number of jBASE files the application thinks it has open at the moment.

<27> Number of jBASE files actually opened by the operating system at the moment.

<28> Any data set by the application using @USER.ROOT

<29> Process Identifier. A string created by the operating system to identify the process. It is O/S specific. Currenly on IBM i-series platform only.

<30> to <40> Reserved.

Attributes 41 onward are multi-valued, one value per perform level, and there are <2> perform levels active.

<41,n> Program name and command line arguments.

<42,n> The line number in jBC the program is currently executing.

<43,n> The source name in jBC the program is currently executing.

<44,n> Not used.

<45,n> Not used.

<46,n> Status of program execution as a readable text string.

<47,n> Status of program execution as an internal integer.

<48,n> User CPU time . Depending upon the hardware this will be either for the entire process or just the single thread.

<49,n> System CPU time. Depending upon the hardware this will be either for the entire process or just the single thread.

<50,n> User CPU time used by any external child processes it might have spawned.

<51,n> System CPU time used by any external child processes it might have spawned.

<52,n> Any data set by the application using @USER.THREAD # @

Use the @ function to position the cursor to a specific point on the terminal screen

COMMAND SYNTAX

@ (col{,row})

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

col and row can be any expression that evaluates to a numeric value.

col specifies, to which column on the screen the cursor should be moved.

row specifies which row (line) on the screen to position the cursor.

Specifying col on its own will locate the cursor to the required column on whichever row it currently occupies.

NOTES

When specified values exceed either of the physical limits of the current terminal, then unpredictable results will occur.

The terminal address starts at (0,0), that being the top left hand corner of the screen.

Cursor addressing will not normally work when directed at a printer. If you wish to build printer independence into your programs, achieve this by accessing the terminfo database through the SYSTEM () function.

EXAMPLE

   FOR I = 1 TO 5
      CRT @(5, I) : "*" :
   NEXT I
   Home = @(0,0) ;* Remember the cursor home position
   CRT Home: "Hi honey, I'm HOME!" :

EXAMPLE 2

Here the screen will be drawn, parts of it redrawn and then cleared:

   size_x = SYSTEM(2) - 5 ; size_y = SYSTEM(3) - 5
   info_x = 1  ;  info_y = size_y + 1
   DIM the_screen(size_x, size_y)
   CRT @(-1)
   MAT the_screen = '*'
   left_offset = 1
   GOSUB DRAW.SCREEN
   MAT the_screen = '#'
   left_offset = INT(size_x / 2)
   GOSUB DRAW.SCREEN
   hole_x = 5  ;  hole_y = 5  ;  hole_len = 5
   GOSUB MAKE.HOLE
   hole_x = left_offset - 5  ;  hole_y = 10  ;  hole_len = 20
   GOSUB MAKE.HOLE
   CRT @(info_x, info_y) : "That's all folks!" : @(-3)
                  ;* -3 clears all to the end of line
   *
   STOP
   *
   DRAW.SCREEN:
      CRT @(info_x, info_y) : 'Drawing ' : the_screen(1, 1) : "'s..."
      FOR i = left_offset TO size_x
         FOR j = 1 TO size_y
            CRT @(i, j) : the_screen(i, j):
         NEXT j
      MSLEEP(100) ;* 0.1 sec
      NEXT i
      MSLEEP(2000)
      RETURN
   *
   MAKE.HOLE:
      CRT @(info_x, info_y) : 'Making a hole at ' : hole_x : '/' : hole_y
      CRT @(hole_x, hole_y) : STR(' ', hole_len)
      MSLEEP(2000)
      RETURN
   END

ABORT

The ABORT statement terminates the current running program and the program that called it.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ABORT {message.number {, expression ...}}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The optional message.number provided with the statement must be a numeric value, which corresponds to a record key in the TAFC error message file.

A single expression or a list of expression(s) may follow the message.number. Where more than one expression is listed, they must be delimited by the use of the comma character. The expression(s) correspond to the parameters that need passing to the error file record to print it.

The optional message.number and expression(s) given with the command are parameters or resultants provided as variables, literal strings, expressions, or functions.

NOTES

Use this statement to terminate the execution of a jBC program together with any calling program. It will then optionally display a message, and return to the shell prompt.

The error file holds the optional message displayed on terminating the program. For successful printing of the message, parameters such as linefeeds, clearscreen, date and literal strings may also be required. Setting the Command Level Restart option can alter operation of this command.

EXAMPLE

* Open a file with random name (just to make sure that it doesn't exist)
   V.FNAME = ''
   FOR V.J = 1 TO 8
      V.RND = RND(26) + 65
      V.FNAME := CHAR(V.RND)        ;* A...Z
   NEXT V.J
   OPEN V.FNAME TO F.RAND ELSE ABORT 201, V.FNAME

Sample program output:

     ∗∗∗ Error [ 201 ] ∗∗
    Unable to open file XCICLJPH

BITRESET

BITRESET resets the value of a specified bit in the local bit table to zero and returns the previous value of the bit.

COMMAND SYNTAX

BITRESET(table_no)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

table_no specifies the position in the table of the bit for reset. If table_no evaluates to zero, it resets all elements in the table to zero and returns the value zero.

NOTES

For each process, it maintains a unique table of 128 bits (numbered 1 to 128) and treats each bit in the table as a two-state flag - the value returned will always be zero or one.

BITRESET returns the previous value of the bit - you can reset and check a flag in one step.

BITRESET also provides some special functions if you use one of the following table_no values:

Code | Description
-1 | resets the BREAK key Inhibit bit.
-2 | resets the Command Level Restart feature.
-3 | resets the Break/End Restart feature.

See also: BITSET

EXAMPLE

    OLD.VALUE = BITRESET(112)
    PRINT OLD.VALUE

If table entry 112 is one, it returns a value of one, resets bit 112 to 0, and prints one. If table entry 112 is zero, returns a value of 0, and prints 0.

CacheGetOption

The CacheGetOption function will return an option of the bucket.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CacheGetOption(bucket,  option)

EXAMPLE

INCLUDE JBC.h
CRT 'CACHE_MAX_SIZE: ': CacheGetOption('bucket1', CACHE_MAX_SIZE)
CRT 'CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD: ': CacheGetOption('bucket1', CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD)
CachePut('bucket1', 'item1', 'value1')
CRT 'CACHE_MAX_SIZE: ': CacheGetOption('bucket1', CACHE_MAX_SIZE)
CRT 'CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD: ': CacheGetOption('bucket1', CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD)

The output is:

    CACHE_MAX_SIZE: 0
    CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD: 0
    CACHE_MAX_SIZE: 1048576
    CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD: 90

NOTES

The bucket should exists otherwise this function returns zeros.

The "option" parameter may have following values:

CACHE_MAX_SIZE: Bucket maximum size in bytes. By default, the bucket size is 1048576. If the size reaches this value, the most outdated data will be purged from the bucket to reduce its size.

CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD: Percentage (from 1 to 100) of a bucket size exceeding of which leads to the bucket purging. By default, it's value is 90. When a bucket size exceeds the (CACHE_MAX_SIZE * CACHE_PURGE_THRESHOLD / 100) value the most outdated data will be purged from the bucket to reduce its size.

This function does not affect statistics of the bucket.

CacheStats

The CacheStats function will return a statistics counter of the specified bucket in the cache.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CacheStats(bucket, counter_id)

EXAMPLE

INCLUDE JBC.h
CachePut('bucket1', 'item1', 'value1')
CachePut('bucket1', 'item2', 'value2')
CacheGet('bucket1', 'item1')
CacheGet('bucket1', 'item3')
CRT "CACHE_HITS: " : CacheStats('bucket1', CACHE_HITS)
CRT "CACHE_GETS: " : CacheStats('bucket1', CACHE_GETS)
CRT "CACHE_PUTS: " : CacheStats('bucket1', CACHE_PUTS)
CRT "CACHE_SIZE: " : CacheStats('bucket1', CACHE_SIZE)
CRT "CACHE_NB_ITEMS: " : CacheStats('bucket1', CACHE_NB_ITEMS)

The output is:

    CACHE_HITS: 1
    CACHE_GETS: 2
    CACHE_PUTS: 2
    CACHE_SIZE: 12
    CACHE_NB_ITEMS: 2

NOTES

The "counter_id" parameter may have following values:

CACHE_HITS: Number of successful hits to the bucket. This counter is incremented by CacheGet function if a requested item exists in the bucket.

CACHE_GETS: Number of reads from the bucket. This counter is incremented by CacheGet on every call.

CACHE_PUTS: Number of writes to the bucket. This counter is incremented by CachePut on every call.

CACHE_SIZE: Total size of the bucket in bytes. This parameter is calculated by adding the lengths of all items of the bucket which have a String.

CACHE_NB_ITEMS: Number of items in the bucket.

This function does not affect statistics of the bucket.

CALL

The CALL statement transfers program execution to an external subroutine.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CALL {@} subroutine.name {(argument{, argument ... })}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The CALL statement transfers program execution to the subroutine called subroutine.name, which can be any valid string either quoted or unquoted.

The CALL @ variant of this statement assumes that subroutine.name is a variable that contains the name of the subroutine to call.

The CALL statement may optionally pass a number of parameters to the target subroutine. These parameters can consist of any valid expression or variable name. If a variable name is used then the called program may return a value to the variable by changing the value of the equivalent variable in its own parameter list.

NOTES

When using an expression to pass a parameter to the subroutine, you cannot use the built-in functions of jBC (such as COUNT), within the expression.

An unlimited number of parameters can be passed to an external subroutine. The number of parameters in the CALL statement must match exactly the number expected in the SUBROUTINE statement declaring the external subroutine, otherwise runtime error is raised.

It is not required that the calling program and the external subroutine be compiled with the same PRECISION. However, any changes to precision in a subroutine will not persist when control returns to the calling program.

Variables passed as parameters to the subroutine may not reside in any COMMON areas declared in the program.

EXAMPLE

A subroutine:

   SUBROUTINE NUM.INCR(P.NUMBER)
* increase the parameter
   P.NUMBER ++
   RETURN
END

A calling program:

   V.ARRAY = 1 :@FM: 2 :@FM: 3 :@FM: 4
   CRT FMT(V.ARRAY, 'MCP')   ;* 1^2^3^4
   V.ARRAY<2> += 1
   CRT FMT(V.ARRAY, 'MCP')  ;* 1^3^3^4 - array element can be processed directly
   CALL NUM.INCR(V.ARRAY<2>)
   CRT FMT(V.ARRAY, 'MCP')   ;* still 1^3^3^4 - passing to a subr doesn't work
   V.VAR = V.ARRAY<2>
   CALL NUM.INCR(V.VAR)
   V.ARRAY<2> = V.VAR
   CRT FMT(V.ARRAY, 'MCP')   ;* now 1^4^3^4 - should use a variable
   V.SUBR = 'NUM.INCR'
   CALL @V.SUBR(V.VAR)       ;* can call a subroutine this way
   CRT V.VAR                 ;* 5
* Dimensioned array is ok as well
   DIM V.DIM.ARR(3)
   V.DIM.ARR(2) = 'NUM.INCR'
   V.I = 2
   CALL @V.DIM.ARR(V.I) (V.VAR)
   CRT V.VAR        ;* 6
* Pass by value rather than by reference - variable keeps its value:
   CALL NUM.INCR((V.VAR))
   CRT V.VAR        ;* 6
* Wrong CALL:
   CALL NUM.INCR(V.VAR, 1)

Output:

    1^2^3^4
    1^3^3^4
    1^3^3^4
    1^4^3^4
    5
    6
    6
     ∗∗ Error [ SUBROUTINE_PARM_ERROR ] ∗∗
    'SUBROUTINE NUM.INCR' called with incorrect arguments , Line 1 , Source test2.b
    Trap from an error message, error message name = SUBROUTINE_PARM_ERROR
    Source changed to .\test2.b
    jBASE debugger->

CALLC

The CALLC command transfers program control to an external function (c.sub.name). The second form of the syntax calls a function whose name is stored in a jBC variable (@var). The program could pass back return values in variables. CALLC arguments can be simple variables or complex expressions, but not arrays. Use CALLC as a command or function.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CALLC c.sub.name [(argument1[,argument2]...)]

CALLC @var [(argument1[,argument2]...)]

Calling a C Program in TAFC

You must link the C program to TAFC before calling it from a BASIC program. Perform the following procedure to prepare TAFC for CALLC:

Write and compile the C program.
Define the C program call interface
Build the runtime version of TAFC (containing the linked C program).
Write, compile, and execute the Basic program

Calling a Function in Windows NT

The CALLC implementation in TAFC for Windows NT or Windows 2000 uses the Microsoft Windows Dynamic Link Library (DLL) facility. This facility allows separate pieces of code to call one another without permanently binding together. Linking between the separate pieces occurs at runtime (rather than compile time) through a DLL interface.

For CALLC, developers create a DLL and then call that DLL from TAFC.

EXAMPLES

In the following example, the called subroutine draws a circle with its center at the twelfth row and twelfth column and a radius of 3:

RADIUS = 3
CENTER = "12,12"
CALLC DRAW.CIRCLE(RADIUS,CENTER)

In the next example, the subroutine name is stored in the variable SUB.NAME, and is indirectly called:

SUB.NAME = DRAW.CIRCLE
CALLC @SUB.NAME(RADIUS,CENTER)

The next example uses, CALLC as a function, assigning the return value of the subroutine PROG.STATUS in the variable RESULT:

RESULT = CALLC PROG.STATUS

CALLJ

The CALLJ command allows BASIC to call a Java method. CALLJ is useful when using third party applications offering a Java API (for example, publish and subscribe, messaging, etc.)

COMMAND SYNTAX

CALLJ packageAndClassName, [$]methodName, param SETTING ret  \
      [ON ERROR] errStatment

In order to use CALLJ, you need:

A Java virtual machine
CLASSPATH environment variable set to point on the class you want to invoke

NOTES

The Java virtual machine is loaded dynamically at runtime, so a compiled basic application has no dependencies on any Java virtual machine. By default, the program will search for:

jvm.dll on Windows platforms

libjvm.sl on HP UNIX

libjvm.so for other platforms

Although it is not usually necessary, it is possible to specify a Java library by setting the JBCJVMLIB environment variable:

Windows: set JBCJVMLIB=jvm.dll AIX: export JBCJVMLIB=libjvm.so

PERFORMANCE CONSIDERATIONS

The first call to CALLJ carries the overhead of loading the Java Virtual Machine into memory. Subsequent calls do not have this overhead. Many additional threads will be created and used by the JVM.

In addition, calls to non static methods carry the overhead of calling the constructor for the class. Wherever possible, static methods should be used.

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

packageAndClassName The "full" class name (e.g., com.jbase.util.utilClass)

methodName The name of the Java method in this class (e.g., "myMethod")

NOTE: If the method is static, you must append a dollay symbol ( $ ) before the name. It will be removed from the method name before calling it.

Param Any parameter (eg DynArray)

EXAMPLE

In Java:

    package mypackage;
//
    public class mytestclass {
        static int i = 0;
        private mytestclass() {
        }
//
        public String mymethod(String s) {
            return ( "Java Received : " + s ) ;
        }
//
        public static String mystaticmethod(String s) {
            i++;
            return s + " "  + i;
        }
    }

To call these methods from jBC:

CALLJ 'mypackage.mytestclass', 'mymethod', p SETTING ret
CRT ret
CALLJ 'mypackage/mytestclass', '$mystaticmethod', p SETTING ret
CRT ret

ON ERROR

Use the SYSTEM(0) variable to manage any errors at the BASIC level, which occur during the call.

This variable can have the following values:

Value | Description
1 | Fatal error creating thread
2 | Cannot create JVM
3 | Cannot find class
4 | Unicode conversion error
5 | Cannot find method
6 | Cannot find object constructor
7 | Cannot instantiate object

EXAMPLE

jBC code using the ON ERROR will look like this:

PROGRAM testcallj
     className = ''
     methodName = ''
     param = ''
     CRT "Please enter a Class Name " :  ;   INPUT className
     CRT "Please enter a Method Name " :  ;  INPUT methodName
     CRT "Please enter a Parameter : "  ; INPUT param
     CALLJ className,methodName, param SETTING ret ON ERROR GOTO errHandler
     CRT "Received batch from Java : " : ret
RETURN
*
errHandler:
     err = SYSTEM(0)
     IF err = 2 THEN
          CRT "Cannot find the JVM.dll !"
          RETURN
     END
     IF err = 3 THEN
          CRT "Class " : className : "doesn't exist !"
          RETURN
     END
*
     IF err = 5 THEN
          CRT "Method " : methodName : "doesn't exist !"
          RETURN
     END
END

The CALLJ function provides access to a JavaVM from within the BASIC environment. For it to be able to start a JavaVM (JVM) the environment needs to know where the JVM is located. Specifically it needs to know where certain libraries are located.

WINDOWS

Windows: looking for 'jvm.dll'

Add "c:1.6.0_33" to the PATH environment variable.

A generic format might be.

UNIX

For UNIX it is possible to configure generic symbolic links to make profiles portable.

Location of JDK export JDKDIR=/opt/java6

Symbolic link for JRE libs /opt/java6/jrelib

Symbolic link for JVM library /opt/java6/jvmlib

Linux

 /opt/java6/jrelib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64

 /opt/java6/jvmlib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64/server

.profile:

Add "/opt/java6/jrelib:/opt/java6/jvmlib" to the LD_LIBRARY_PATH

HP-UX

 /opt/java6/jrelib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/IA64W

 /opt/java6/jvmlib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/IA64W/server

 .profile:

Add "/opt/java6/jrelib:/opt/java6/jvmlib" to the SHLIB_PATH

AIX (IBM JDK)

 /opt/java6/jrelib   -> /opt/java6/jre/bin

 /opt/java6/jvmlib   -> /opt/java6/jre/bin/classic

 .profile:

Add "/opt/java6/jrelib:/opt/java6/jvmlib" to the LIBPATH

Solaris SPARC

 /opt/java6/jrelib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/sparc

 /opt/java6/jvmlib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/sparc/server

 .profile:

Add "opt/java6/jrelib:/opt/java6/jvmlib" to the LD_LIBRARY_PATH

Solaris AMD64

 /opt/java6/jrelib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64

 /opt/java6/jvmlib   -> /opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64/server

 .profile:

Add "opt/java6/jrelib:/opt/java6/jvmlib" to the LD_LIBRARY_PATH

EXAMPLES using JVM WITHOUT symbolic links as above:

Linux: looking for 'libjvm.so'

    Add 2 directories to LD_LIBRARY_PATH.
    /opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64/server:/opt/java6/jre/lib/amd64

Solaris: looking for 'libjvm.so'

    Add 2 directories to LD_LIBRARY_PATH.
    /opt/java6/jre/lib/sparc/server:/opt/java6/jre/lib/sparc

HP-UX 11: looking for 'libjvm.sl'

    Add 2 directories to SHLIB_PATH.
   /opt/java6/jre/lib/IA64W/server:/opt/java6/jre/lib/IA64W

OPTIONS

JBCJVMLIB

If the search for the library appears incorrect for your platform, then you can override it by setting the JBCJVMLIB environment variable.

e.g. export JBCJVMLIB=jvm.shared_lib

and then CALLJ will try to locate the library 'jvm.shared_lib' at runtime.

JBCJVMPOLICYFILE

You can specify a policy file for the JMV. The policy for a Java application environment (specifying which permissions are available for code from various sources) is represented by a Policy object. More specifically, it is represented by a Policy subclass providing an implementation of the abstract methods in the Policy class (which is in the java.security package). You can override it by setting the JBCJVMPOLICYFILE environment variable.

The source location for the default policy information is:

WINDOWS

    %TAFC_HOME%\config\policy.all

UNIX

    $TAFC_HOME/config/policy.all

e.g. "export JBCJVMPOLICYFILE=/usr/jbase/mypolicy.all"

JBCJVMENCODING

Internally, the Java virtual machine always operates with data in Unicode. However, as data transfers to or from the Java virtual machine, the Java virtual machine converts the data to other encodings. If the you want to change the default encoding of the JVM on your platform, then you can override it by setting the JBCJVMENCODING environment variable.

e.g. "export JBCJVMENCODING=Cp1257"

JBCJVMNOOPTS

Internally, CALLJ is optimized to start the JVM with options (see the table below). If you do not want to pass these options for the JVM, then you can override it by setting the JBCJVMNOOPTS environment variable. In this case no more options will be passed to the JVM.

JBCIBMJDK

On Linux we assumed that the Sun Java JDK would be used and the JVM options reflect this. But as they are not compatible with the IBM JDK you can set the JBCIBMJDK option to allow the running of the IBM JDK for Linux.

DEFAULT OPTIONS

Platform | Parameter
Win32: | -Xrs
Solaris: | -XX:+AllowUserSignalHandlers
Linux: | -Xrs -XX:+AllowUserSignalHandlers
AIX 64 bits: | -Xrs -d64
HPUX 64 bits: | -Xrs -XX:+AllowUserSignalHandlers

JBCJVMOPT[1..5]

If the you want to pass some options for the JVM, then set the JBCJVMOPT[1..5] environment variable

e.g. "export JBCJVMOPT1=-Xrs"

JBCJVMOPTS

Allows many options to be set within one variable. e.g. export JBCJVMOPTS="-Xrs -Xms256M -Xmx512M"

KNOWN LIMITATIONS

HP-UX

There is a problem with HP-UX due to its dynamic loader. See man dlopen(3C) for detail of the TLS limitation.

This means that the JVM library must be linked against the calling program, there are no known problems caused by this.

'ldd progname' lists current external library references and we need to add libjvm.

The symptom looks like this:

    JVM: dl_error [Can't dlopen a library containing Thread Local Storage: libjvm.sl]

If the program is built with the required link as below then it works.

    jbc -Jo callj.b -ljvm -L/opt/java6/jre/lib/IA64W/server

If the CALLJ statement is inside a subroutine, then the program that calls the subroutine must be built as above.

CALLONEXIT

The CALLONEXIT function call allows you to specify the name of a SUBROUTINE to call when the program terminates.

COMMAND SYNTAX

rc = CALLONEXIT('ErrorExit')

The subroutine definition would look like this

SUBROUTINE CALLONEXIT(parm1)

You can add parameters to the error subroutine by adding multi-values to the parameter to CALLONEXIT, which are passed to the called subroutine in the first parameter.

If you execute CALLONEXIT multiple times with the same subroutine name, it discards other calls.

If you execute CALLONEXIT multiple times with a different subroutine name, then upon exit multiple subroutines will be called in the order that CALLONEXIT was called.

EXAMPLES

For example, consider the simple programs below. The program enters the debugger. If at this point the login session terminates for any reason (the line drops, the program is killed, the user enters 'off' at the debugger prompt) , the two specified subroutines (ErrorExit and EndProgram) will still be called just as they would if the program were allowed to terminate normally.

PROGRAM PROG1
rc = CALLONEXIT('ErrorExit')
EXECUTE "PROG2"

PROGRAM PROG2
rc = CALLONEXIT('EndProgram')
DEBUG

All efforts are made to call the subroutine under all circumstances. However, if a SIGKILL (signal 9) terminates the program, which cannot be trapped, it does not call the subroutine. This is a feature of operating systems, not a limitation. In addition, if the program terminates due to say a memory error, then calling the subroutines depends upon how badly the memory error has corrupted the memory.

CASE

The CASE statement allows the programmer to execute a particular sequence of instructions based upon the results of a series of test expressions.

COMMAND SYNTAX

    BEGIN CASE
    CASE expression statement(s)
    CASE expression
    *statement(s)
    *. . .
    END CASE

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The BEGIN CASE and END CASE statements bound the CASE structure. Within this block, an arbitrary number of CASE expression statements may exist followed by any number of jBC statements. The expression should evaluate to a TRUE or FALSE result. The evaluation of each expression at execution time is in order. If the expression returns a TRUE result, it then executes the statements below. On completion of the associated statements, execution will resume at the first statement following the END CASE.

NOTES:

A default action (to trap error conditions for instance) may be introduced by using an expression that is always TRUE, such as "CASE 1". This should always be the last expression in the CASE block.

EXAMPLE

   V.STRING = 'B'
   GOSUB CHK.IT
   V.STRING = 'ABC'
   GOSUB CHK.IT
   STOP
*
CHK.IT:
*
   BEGIN CASE
   CASE V.STRING EQ 'A'
      CRT 'an A'
   CASE  V.STRING EQ 'B'
      CRT 'a B'
   CASE V.STRING EQ 'C'
      CRT 'a C'
   CASE 1
      CRT 'neither A nor B nor C'
   END CASE
   RETURN
END

Output:

    a B
    neither A nor B nor C
     

CATALOG

Cataloging and Running your Programs

Use the CATALOG command to create UNIX executables and shared libraries from the application source code. Once you have cataloged your programs, you can run them like any other command on the system.

The RUN command which is sometimes used to execute compiled jBC programs without cataloging them can still be used but is really only maintained for compatibility. Whenever possible, you should catalog your programs rather than RUN them.

The CATALOG command should be executed from the application directory rather than using link names and the application id should be used. The reasons for executing the CATALOG command from the application directory and application id are that the .profile script will have set up the required environment variables correctly and that the correct file permission will be used when creating and deleting UNIX executables and directories.

The format of the CATALOG command is as follows.

    CATALOG SourceFilename Itemlist

When first invoked the CATALOG command will create a $HOME/bin directory into which the UNIX executables will be placed. A $HOME/lib directory will also be created into which any subroutines will be placed. The lib directory contains a jLibDefinition file, which describes how to build the subroutines into shared libraries. The entries in the jLibDefinition file are described below:

Entry | Description
libname | naming convention for shared object files.
exportname | export list of shared objects. Used as cross
| reference to find subroutine functions.
maxsize | maximum size of a shared object library before
| creating another.

When the maximum size of a shared library object is reached then a new shared library object will be created by the CATALOG command. The new shared library objects are named according to the definition of libname and are numbered sequentially. For example:

libname=lib%a%n.so

where

%a = account or directory name

%n = number in sequence.

If subroutines were cataloged in the user account name, fred then the shared object libraries produced would be named, libfred0.so libfred1.so libfred2.so and so on.

Note: To guard against libraries being cataloged incorrectly, perhaps under the wrong user account name, the definition of libname should be changed to libfred%n.so. This will ensure that any shared objects are created using the proper user account name.

The shared library objects,.so files, contain the UNIX executables for subroutine source code. The shared library objects are linked at runtime by the TAFC call function, which utilises the dynamic linker programming interface. The dynamic linker will link shared libraries at the start of program execution time, or when requested by the TAFC call function. For example, each executable created using the TAFC compiler will be linked with the TAFC jEDI library functions, libjedi.so, at compilation time. This shared library enables database record retrieval and update and will be loaded into memory by the dynamic linker when an application executable starts execution. However the shared library containing any subroutines required by the executing program will only be loaded into memory when initially requested by the subroutine call. Only one copy of any shared library is required in memory at any time, thus reducing program memory requirements.

The $HOME/lib directory also contains a directory where all the subroutine objects, .o files, are held. These are required for making the shared library, .so files.

The $HOME/lib directory also contains an export list, .el file, built by the CATALOG command, which is used as a cross reference when dynamically linking shared objects at run time.

The main application program executables are placed into the $HOME/bin directory.

To enable the application executables to be found the $HOME/bin path should be added to the PATH environment variable.

To enable the executing application to call the correct application subroutines the JBCOBJECTLIST or LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment variable should be assigned to the application shared library path, $HOME/lib. If the main application program or any subroutine programs make calls to subroutines in other directories then the path of the shared library directories should also be added to the JBCOBJECTLIST or LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment variable.

It is recommended that executables or subroutines of the same name are not available from different directories. This can make application execution very confusing and is reliant on assigning the lib or bin directories to the environment variable in the correct sequence. The assignment of the environment variables should be included and exported in the .profile script file.

Executables and shared library objects can be removed from the bin and l ib directories by using the DECATALOG command.

CHAIN

The CHAIN statement exits the current program and transfers process control to the program defined by the expression. Process control will never return to the originating program.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CHAIN expression

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The expression should evaluate to a valid UNIX or Windows command (this may be another jBC program). The command string may be suffixed with the (I option, which will cause any COMMON variables in the current program to be inherited by the new program (providing it is a jBC program).

NOTES

There are no restrictions to the CHAIN statement and you may CHAIN from anywhere to anywhere. However, it is advisable that your program follows a logical path easily seen by another programmer. If the program, which contains the CHAIN command (the current program) was called from a JCL program, and the program to be executed (the target program) is another jBC program, control will return to the original JCL program when the target program terminates. If the target program is a JCL program, control will return to the command shell when the JCL program terminates.

EXAMPLES

    CHAIN "OFF" ;* exit via the OFF command

    ! Prog1
    COMMON A,B
    A = 50 ; B = 100
    CHAIN "NEWPROG (I"

    ! NEWPROG
    COMMON I,J
    ! I and J inherited
    CRT I,J

COMMON

The COMMON statement declares a list of variables and matrices that can be shared among various programs. There can be many common areas including a default, unnamed common area.

COMMAND SYNTAX

COMMON { /CommonName/ } variable {, variable ... }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The list of variables should not have been declared or referenced previously in the program file. The compiler will detect any bad declarations and display suitable warning or error messages. If the common area declared with the statement is to be named then the first entry in the list should be a string, delimited by the / character.

NOTES

The compiler will not, by default, check that variables declared in COMMON statements are initialized before they have been used as this may be beyond the scope of this single source code check. The -JCi option, when specified to the jBC compiler, will force this check to be applied to common variables as well. The initialization of named common is controlled in the Config_EMULATE file.

Variables declared without naming the common area may only be shared between the program and its subroutines (unless CHAIN is used). Variables declared in a named common area may be shared across program boundaries.

Dimensioned arrays are declared and dimensioned within the COMMON statement.

EXAMPLE

   COMMON /MY.COMM/ V.VAR1
   CRT ASSIGNED(V.VAR1)   ;* depends on emulation (e.g. 1 for prime)
   CRT V.VAR1             ;* first run: again depends on emulation
                          ;* (e.g. 0 for prime), second run: YES
   CRT ASSIGNED(V.VAR2)   ;* 0
   V.VAR1 = 'YES'
   V.VAR2 = 'NO'

NOTE

When a COMMON area is used in different programs or subroutines, it has to be declared in each of them. Variable names can be different but their number has to be the same.

EXAMPLE

Program test.b:

   COMMON /MY.AREA/ global_var, global_dyn_array
   global_var = 42
   EXECUTE 'test2'

Program test2.b:

   COMMON /MY.AREA/ my_var, my_dyn_array
   CRT my_var

Run program test:

    42

NOTE

It's a good idea to put COMMON areas declaration for particular task to an insert file and include it into every relevant source file.

EXAMPLE

File I_MYTASK.COMMON:

   COMMON /MY.AREA/ global_var, global_dyn_array

Program test.b:

   $INSERT I_MYTASK.COMMON
   &nbsp;
   global_var = 42
   EXECUTE 'test2'

Program test2.b:

   $INSERT I_MYTASK.COMMON
   &nbsp;
   CRT global_var
   CRT ASSIGNED(global_dyn_array)

Run program test (prime emulation):

    42
    1

r83 emulation:

    42
    0

NOTE

If number of variables in COMMON area changes, all relevant source files are to be recompiled.

CONVERT

The CONVERT function is the function form of the CONVERT statement. It performs exactly the same function but may also operate on an expression rather than being restricted to variables.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CONVERT(expression1, expression2, expression3)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 is the string to which the conversion will apply.

expression2 is the list of all characters to translate in expression1.

expression3 is the list of characters that will be converted to.

NOTE: For Prime, Universe and Unidata emulations:

expression1 is the list of all characters to translate in expression1.

expression2 is the list of characters that will be converted to.

expression3 is the string to which the conversion will apply.

See also: CONVERT (STATEMENT)

EXAMPLE

* compile this program under same emulation that you're testing
   IF NOT(GETENV('JBCEMULATE', jbc_emu)) THEN
      CRT 'Emulation setting not found'
      STOP
   END
   *
   the_string = 'ABCCCDEFCDYZ'
   IF jbc_emu = 'prime' THEN
      the_result = CONVERT('CEY', '+-*', the_string)
   END ELSE
      the_result = CONVERT(the_string, 'CEY', '+-*')
   END
   *
   CRT jbc_emu, the_result                ;* e.g. prime AB+++D-F+D*Z

COUNTS

Use the COUNTS function to count the number of times a substring is repeated in each element of a dynamic array. The result is a new dynamic array whose elements are the counts corresponding to the elements in the dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

COUNTS(dynamic.array, substring)

dynamic.array specifies the dynamic array whose elements are to be searched.

substring is an expression that evaluates to the substring to be counted. substring can be a character string, a constant, or a variable. Each character in an element is matched to substring only once. Therefore, when substring is longer than one character and a match is found, the search continues with the character following the matched substring. No part of the matched element is recounted toward another match. If substring does not appear in an element, a 0 value is returned. If substring is an empty string, the number of characters in the element is returned. If substring is null, the COUNTS function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message. If any element in dynamic.array is null, null is returned.

EXAMPLE

ARRAY= "A" :@VM: "AA" :@SM: "AAAAA"
PRINT COUNTS(ARRAY, 'A')
PRINT COUNTS(ARRAY, 'AA')

The output of this program is:

    1]2\5
    0]1\2

CREATE

Use the CREATE statement after an OPENSEQ statement to create a record in a jBASE directory file or to create a UNIX or DOS file. CREATE creates the record or file if the OPENSEQ statement fails.

An OPENSEQ statement for the specified file.variable must be executed before the CREATE statement to associate the pathname or record ID of the file to be created with the file.variable. If file.variable is null, the CREATE statement fails and the program enters the debugger.

Use the CREATE statement when OPENSEQ cannot find a record or file to open and the next operation is to be a READSEQ or READBLK. If the first file operation is a WRITESEQ,it creates the record or file if it does not exist.

If the record or file is created, it executes the THEN statements; if no record or file is created, it executes the ELSE statements.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CREATE file.variable { THEN statements [ ELSE statements ] | ELSE statements }

EXAMPLE

In the following example, RECORD does not yet exist. When OPENSEQ fails to open RECORD to the file variable FILE, the CREATE statement creates RECORD in the type 1 file DIRFILE and opens it to the file variable FILE.

INCLUDE JBC.h
   out_dir = '.'  ;  out_file = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ out_dir, out_file TO f_out THEN
      WEOFSEQ f_out
   END ELSE
      CREATE f_out ELSE CRT 'File create error'  ;  STOP
      CRT 'File created'
   END
   WRITESEQ 'ABCDEFabcdef' TO f_out ELSE
      CRT 'Write error'
      STOP
   END
   CLOSESEQ f_out
   OSREAD the_content FROM out_dir : DIR_DELIM_CH : out_file ELSE NULL
   CRT the_content        ;* ABCDEFabcdef

CRT

The CRT statement sends data directly to the terminal, even if a PRINTER ON statement is currently active.

COMMAND SYNTAX

CRT expression {, expression..} {:}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

An expression can evaluate to any data type. The CRT statement will convert the result to a string type for printing. Expressions separated by commas will be sent to the screen separated by a tab character.

The CRT statement will append a newline sequence to the final expression unless it is terminated with a colon (":") character.

NOTES

As the expression can be any valid expression, it may have output formatting applied to it.

A jBC program is normally executed using buffered output mode. This means that data is not flushed to the terminal screen unless a newline sequence is printed or terminal input is requested. This makes it very efficient. However you can force output to be flushed to the terminal by printing a null character CHAR (0). This has the same effect as a newline sequence but without affecting screen output.

For compatibility, use DISPLAY in place of CRT.

EXAMPLES

   V.VAR = 5
   CRT V.VAR           ;* 5
   V.VAR ++
   CRT V.VAR           ;* 6 (on the next line)
   V.VAR ++
   CRT ''              ;* start a new line
   CRT V.VAR           ;* 7 (2 lines below "6")
   V.RESULT = 50
   CRT 'The result: ':
   CRT V.RESULT        ;* will output: "The result: 50" on the same line
   MSLEEP(3000)
   CRT @(-1)                    ;* clears the screen and homes the cursor
   CRT @(40, 12):'Hello'        ;* will start output at row 11, column 39
   CRT ''
   V.NUM = 39
   V.STRING = 'In the year of'
   CRT V.STRING : ' ' : V.NUM    ;* In the year of 39
   CRT V.STRING, V.NUM           ;* In the year of  39
   V.LINE = '39R'
   V.STRING = 'In the year of'
   CRT V.STRING V.LINE             ;* same as FMT(V.STRING, '39R')
   V.VAR = 5
   CRT V.VAR > 1           ;* Result of an expression (1 in this case)
   CRT @SYS.BELL           ;* rings the bell

DATA

The DATA statement stacks the series of expressions on a terminal input FIFO stack. Terminal input statements will then treat this data as if entered at the keyboard.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DATA expression {, expression ...}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The expression may evaluate to any data type; views each comma-separated expression as one line of terminal input.

NOTES

The data stacked for input will subsequently be treated as input by any jBC program. Therefore use it before PERFORM/EXECUTE, CHAIN or any other method of transferring program execution. Use also to stack input for the currently executing program; do not use to stack input back to an executing program.

When a jBC program detects stacked data, it is taken as keyboard input until the stack is exhausted. The program will then revert to the terminal device for subsequent terminal input.

Stacked data delimited by field marks (xFE) will be treated as a series of separate terminal inputs.

See also: CLEARDATA

EXAMPLE

Program test.b:

   DATA '12345'
   DATA '67890'
   EXECUTE 'test2'

Program test2.b:

   INPUT V.DATA1
   INPUT V.DATA2
   CRT 'I got ' : V.DATA1 : ' and ' : V.DATA2

If test2 is run by itself, it asks for user input. If test is run, the output is:

    I got 12345 and 67890

DECRYPT

The DECRYPT function decrypts strings.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DECRYPT(string, key, method)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

string specifies the string to be decrypted.

Key is the value used to decrypt the string. Its use depends on method.

method is a value, which indicates the encryption mechanism to use (see below).

The ENCRYPT and DECRYPT functions that are part of jBC now support the following cipher methods (Defined in JBC.h)

Value | Description
JBASE_CRYPT_GENERAL | General-purpose encryption scheme
JBASE_CRYPT_ROT13 | Simple ROT13 algorithm. (Key not used)
JBASE_CRYPT_XOR11 | XOR MOD11 algorithm. Uses the first
| character of a key as a seed value
JBASE_CRYPT_RC2 | RC2 algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_DES | DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_3DES | Three Key, Triple DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH | Blowfish algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_AES | AES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64 | (See below)

BASE64 is not really an encryption method, but more of an encoding. The reason for this is that the output of an encryption often results in a binary string. It allows binary data to be represented as a character string. BASE64 operation is not required but is performed in addition to the primary algorithm. e.g. JBASE_CRYPT_RC2_BASE64

ENCRYPT with this method is the same as a DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_RC2 followed by DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64.

DECRYPT with this method is the same as a DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64 followed by DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_RC2.

Value | Description
JBASE_CRYPT_RC2_BASE64 | RC2 algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_DES_BASE64 | DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_3DES_BASE64 | Triple DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH_BASE64 | Blowfish algorithm

NOTES

See also: ENCRYPT

EXAMPLES

INCLUDE JBC.h
//
IF DECRYPT('rknzcyr', '', JBASE_CRYPT_ROT13) = "example" THEN
  CRT "ROT13 ok"
END
//
IF ENCRYPT('g{ehvkm', '9', JBASE_CRYPT_XOR11) = "example" THEN
  CRT "XOR.MOD11 ok"
END
//
cipher = JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH_BASE64
key    = "Our Very Secret Key"
str    = "String to encrypt"
enc = ENCRYPT( str, key, cipher )
CRT "Encrypted: " : enc
dec = DECRYPT( enc, key, cipher )
CRT "Decrypted: " : dec

Displays as output:

    ROT13 ok
    XOR.MOD11 ok
    Encrypted: xuy6DXxUkD32spyfsKEvUtXrsjP7mC+R
    Decrypted: String to encrypt

DEFC

Use the DEFC statement to declare an external C function to the jBC compiler, define its arguments, and return types. The DEFC statement assumes that the C functions will need to manipulate jBC variables and hence will also require the thread data pointer. As such, all C functions require recoding to include the data pointer as an argument to the C function. The location of the data pointer argument depends upon the function return type.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DEFC {FuncType} FuncName ({ArgType {, ArgType ...}})

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

FuncType and ArgType are selected from one of INT, FLOAT or VAR. FuncType specifies the type of result that the function will return. Assumes INT if FuncType is omitted. The optional list of ArgTypes specifies the argument types that the C function will expect. The compiler must know this in advance, as it will automatically perform type conversions on these arguments.

EXAMPLE

    #include <jsystem.h>
    #include <assert.h>
    //
    #ifdef DPSTRUCT_DEF
    #define JBASEDP       DPSTRUCT ∗dp,
    #else
    #define JBASEDP
    #endif
    //
    VAR ∗MyString(VAR ∗Result, JBASEDP  VAR ∗VarPtr)
    {
        char ∗Ptr;
        assert(dp != NULL);
        Ptr = (char ∗) CONV_SFB(VarPtr);
        printf("MyString: %s - %d\n", Ptr, strlen(Ptr) );
        STORE_VBI(Result, strlen(Ptr) );
        return(Result);
    }
    //
    INT32 MyCalc(INT32 Value1, INT32 Value2)
    {
        INT32  Result;
        Result =  (Value1 / Value2);
        printf("MyCalc: %d\n", Result);
        return(Result);
    }

NOTES

Compile a DEFC for each C function before making any reference to it else the compiler will not recognize the function name.

The function is called in the same manner, as it would be in a C program, which means it can be used as if it was an intrinsic function it as a standalone function call causes the compiler to generate code that ignores any returned values.

When passing jBC variables to a C function, you must utilize the predefined macros to access the various data types it contains. C functions are particularly useful for increasing the performance of tight loops that perform specific functions. The jBC compiler must cater for any eventuality within a loop (such as the controlling variable changing from integer to floating point). A dedicated C function can ignore such events, if they are guaranteed not to happen.

The jBC programmer may freely ignore the type of argument used when invoking the C function, as the jBC compiler will automatically perform type conversion.

DEFFUN

Use the DEFFUN statement to declare an external jBC function to the jBC compiler and optionally define its arguments. Use DEFFUN in the program that calls the function.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DEFFUN FuncName ({ { MAT } Argument1, { MAT } Argument2...})

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

FuncName is the name used to define the function. It must be the same as the source file name.

Argument specifies a value passed to the function by the calling program. To pass an array, the keyword you must use the MAT before the argument name. These parameters are optional (as indicated in the command syntax) but can be specified for clarity. Note that if the arguments are not initialized somewhere in the program you will receive a compiler warning.

NOTES

The DEFFUN statement identifies a user-written function to the jBC compiler, which must be present in each program that calls the function, before the function is called. A hidden argument is passed to the function so that a value can be returned to the calling program. The return value is set in the function using the RETURN (value) statement. If the RETURN statement specifies no value then the function returns an empty string.

EXAMPLE 1

DEFFUN Add()
A = 10
B = 20
sum = Add(A, B)
PRINT sum
X = RND(42)
Y = RND(24)
PRINT Add(X, Y)

FUNCTION Add(operand1, operand2)
result = operand1 + operand2
RETURN(result)

DEL

Use the DEL statement to remove a specified element of a dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DEL variable<expression1{, expression2{, expression3}}>

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The variable can be any previously assigned variable or matrix element. The expressions must evaluate to a numeric value or a runtime error will occur.

expression1 specifies the field in the array to operate upon and must be present.

expression2 specifies the multivalue within the field to operate upon and is an optional parameter.

expression3 is optionally present when expression2 has been included. It specifies which subvalue to delete within the specified multivalue.

NOTES

Truncates non-integer values for any of the expressions to integers

Ignores invalid numeric values for the expressions without warning

The command operates within the scope specified, i.e. if specifying only a field then it deletes the entire field (including its multivalues and subvalues). If specifying a subvalue, then it deletes only the subvalue leaving its parent multivalue and field intact.

EXAMPLE

   Numbers = ''
   FOR I = 1 TO 20
      Numbers<I> = I   ;*generate numbers
   NEXT I
   FOR I = 19 TO 1 STEP -2
      DEL Numbers<I>   ;* remove odd numbers
   NEXT I
   CRT CHANGE(Numbers, @FM, '>')  ;* 2>4>6>8>10>12>14>16>18>20

DIMENSION

Use the DIM statement to declare arrays to the compiler before referencing.

COMMAND SYNTAX

DIM{ENSION} variable(number{, number... }){, variable(number {,number...}) ...}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The variable may be any valid variable name neither declared nor previously used. The numbers define the size of each dimension and must be either constants or the subject of an EQUATE statement. A single DIM statement may declare a number of arrays by separating their declarations with a comma.

NOTES

Declare the array before it is referenced in the program source (compilation as opposed to execution). If using a variable as an undeclared dimensioned array the compiler will display an error message.

Do not use the array variable as a normal variable or dynamic array before dimensioning, as the compiler will detect this as an error.

A dimension size may not be specified as one as this has no logical meaning. The compiler will detect this as a warning.

When arrays are referenced directly as in A = Array(7), the compiler will optimize the reference as if it was a single undimensioned variable.

See also: COMMON

EXAMPLES

   DIMENSION V.ARRAY(10)
   MAT V.ARRAY = '!'
   V.ARRAY(5) = '?'
   FOR V.I = 1 TO 10
      CRT V.ARRAY(V.I):          ;* !!!!?!!!!!
   NEXT V.I

   DIM V.DIM3(2, 3, 4)
   MAT V.DIM3 = 1
   V.DIM3(1,2,1) *= 2
   CRT ''
   CRT V.DIM3(1,2,1)             ;* 2
   CRT V.DIM3(1,2)               ;* still 2
   CRT V.DIM3(1,20,1)            ;* runtime error ARRAY_SUBS

ENCRYPT

The ENCRYPT function encrypts strings.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ENCRYPT(string, key, method)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

string specifies the string for encryption.

key is the value used to encrypt the string. Its use depends on method.

method is a value, which indicates the encryption mechanism to use (See below):

The ENCRYPT and DECRYPT functions that are part of jBC now support the following cipher methods (Defined in JBC.h)

Value | Description
JBASE_CRYPT_GENERAL | General-purpose encryption scheme
JBASE_CRYPT_ROT13 | Simple ROT13 algorithm. (Key not used)
JBASE_CRYPT_XOR11 | XOR MOD11 algorithm. Uses the first character of
| a key as a seed value.
JBASE_CRYPT_RC2 | RC2 algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_DES | DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_3DES | Three Key, Triple DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH | Blowfish algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_AES | AES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64 | (See below)

BASE64 is more of an encoding method rather than an encryption method. The reason for this is that the output of an encryption often results in a binary string, which allows the representation of binary data as a character string. Although not required the BASE64 operation is performed in addition to the primary algorithm. E.g. JBASE_CRYPT_RC2_BASE64

ENCRYPT with this method is the same as an ENCRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_RC2 followed by ENCRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64.

DECRYPT with this method is the same as a DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_BASE64 followed by DECRYPT with method JBASE_CRYPT_RC2.

Value | Description
JBASE_CRYPT_RC2_BASE64 | RC2 algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_DES_BASE64 | DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_3DES_BASE64 | Triple DES algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH_BASE64 | Blowfish algorithm
JBASE_CRYPT_AES_BASE64 | AES algorithm

NOTES

See also: DECRYPT.

EXAMPLES

INCLUDE JBC.h
IF DECRYPT('rknzcyr', '', JBASE_CRYPT_ROT13) = "example" THEN
CRT "ROT13 ok"
END
//
IF ENCRYPT('g{ehvkm', '9', JBASE_CRYPT_XOR11) = "example" THEN
CRT "XOR.MOD11 ok"
END
//
cipher = JBASE_CRYPT_BLOWFISH_BASE64
key    = "Our Very Secret Key"
str    = "String to encrypt"
enc = ENCRYPT( str, key, cipher )
CRT "Encrypted: " : enc
dec = DECRYPT( enc, key, cipher )
CRT "Decrypted: " : dec

Displays as output:

    ROT13 ok
    XOR.MOD11 ok
    Encrypted: xuy6DXxUkD32spyfsKEvUtXrsjP7mC+R
    Decrypted: String to encrypt

Hashing

The ENCRYPT function now supports SHA-2 hashing algorithms.

JBC.h define | Hashing algorithm
JBASE_SECUREHASH_SHA256 | SHA-2 family hashing algorithm
JBASE_SECUREHASH_SHA256_BASE64 | SHA256 with BASE64

Hashing Example

INCLUDE JBC.h
Key = "" ;* unused for hashing
EncryptType = JBASE_SECUREHASH_SHA256_BASE64
StrOut = ENCRYPT(StrIn, Key, EncryptType)

NOTES

See also: DECRYPT.

See also: Wiki

ENTER

The ENTER statement unconditionally passes control to another executable program.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ENTER program_name

ENTER @variable_name

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

program_name is the name of the program for execution. The use of single or double quotes to surround program_name is optional.

@ specifies that the program name is contained in a named variable.

variable_name is the name of the variable, which contains the program name.

NOTES

The jBC COMMON data area can be passed to another jBC program by specifying the option "I" after the program name. Pass the COMMON data area only to another jBC program.

Use ENTER to execute any type of program.

If the program which contains the ENTER command (the current program) was called from a JCL program, and the program for execution (the target program) is another jBC program, control will return to the original JCL program when the target program terminates. If the target program is a JCL program, control will return to the command shell when the JCL program terminates.

EXAMPLES

ENTER "menu"

ProgName = "UPDATE"
ENTER @ProgName

EQUATE

Use EQUATE to declare a symbol equivalent to a literal, variable or simple expression.

COMMAND SYNTAX

EQU{ATE} symbol TO expression

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

symbol is the name of the symbol to use; can be any name that would be valid for a variable.

expression can be a literal, a variable or a simple expression.

NOTES

Sensible use of EQUATEd symbols can make your program easier to maintain, easier to read, and more efficient.

Efficiency can be enhanced because the address of an EQUATEd value is computed during compilation and is substituted for each occurrence of the symbol name. Unlike the address of a variable, which must be computed for each access during run time, the address of a symbol is always known. This significantly reduces the processing overhead involved in accessing a particular value. See also: the example for a more detailed explanation of the other benefits.

Enhance Readability by referring to say, QTY rather than INV_LINE(4). You would simply "EQUATE QTY TO INV_LINE(4)" at an early stage in the program. This can also help with maintenance of the program, particularly in situations where record layouts might change. For example, if the quantity field moves to INV_LINE(6), you only have to change one line in your program.

EXAMPLE

   DIM NV_LINE(10)
   MAT NV_LINE = 100
   COMMON FLAG
   EQUATE NO_CHARGE TO FLAG
   EQUATE CR TO CHAR (13), TRUE TO 1, FALSE TO 0
   EQUATE PRICE TO NV_LINE(7), TAX TO 0.175
   EQUATE DASHES TO "-------"
   IF NO_CHARGE = TRUE THEN PRICE = 0
   CRT "Tax = ":PRICE * TAX:CR:DASHES

Output:

    Tax = 17.5
    -------

EREPLACE

Use the EREPLACE function to replace substring in an expression with another substring. If you do not specify an occurrence, it replaces each occurrence of a substring.

COMMAND SYNTAX

EREPLACE(expression, substring, replacement [,occurrence [,begin] ] )

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

occurrence specifies the number of occurrences of substring to replace. To replace all occurrences, specify occurrence as a number less than 1. begin specifies the first occurrence to replace. If begin is omitted or less than one, it defaults to one. If substring is an empty string, replacement is prefixed to expression. If replacement is an empty string, it removes all occurrences of substring. If expression evaluates to null, it returns null. If substring, replacement, occurrence, or begin evaluates to null, the EREPLACE function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message. The EREPLACE function behaves like the CHANGE function except when substring evaluates to an empty string.

EXAMPLE

A = "AAABBBCCCDDDBBB"
PRINT EREPLACE(A,'BBB', 'ZZZ')
PRINT EREPLACE(A, '', 'ZZZ')
PRINT EREPLACE(A, 'BBB', '')

The output of this program is:

    AAAZZZCCCDDDZZZ
    ZZZAAABBBCCCDDDBBB
    AAACCCDDD

EXECUTE

The EXECUTE or PERFORM statement allows the currently executing program to pause and execute any other UNIX/NT program, including another jBC program or a TAFC command.

COMMAND SYNTAX

EXECUTE | PERFORM expression { CAPTURING variable}  \
    { RETURNING | SETTING variable} { PASSLIST {expression}}  \
    { RTNLIST {variable}}{ PASSDATA variable} { RTNDATA variable}

Executes external programs or OS commands; you can intercept screen output and error messages from any program. Passes data, dynamic arrays and lists to executed jBC programs.

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The PERFORMed expression can be formed from any TAFC construct. The system will not verify that the command exists before executing it. Use a new Bourne Shell to execute a command (sh) by default. The shell type can be changed by preceding the command with a CHAR(255) concatenated with either "k", "c", or "s" to signify the Korn shell, C shell or Bourne Shell.

Variables used to pass data to the executed program should have been assigned to a value before using. You can use any variable name to receive data.

CAPTURING variable

The capturing clause will capture any output that the executing program would normally send to the terminal screen and place it in the variable specified. A field mark in the variable replaces every newline normally sent to the terminal.

RETURNING variable or SETTING variable

The returning and setting clauses are identical. Both clauses will capture the output associated with any error messages the executing program issues. The first field of the variable will be set to the exit code of the program.

PASSLIST variable

The PASSLIST clause allows TAFC programs to exchange lists or dynamic arrays between them. The variable should contain the list that the program wishes to pass to the TAFC program it is executing. The program to be executed should be able to process lists, otherwise the list will just be ignored. If the variable name is not specified then the clause will pass the default select list to the executing program.

RTNLIST variable

If the executed program sets up a list then use the RTNLIST clause to place that list into a specified variable. It places the list in the default list variable if omitted.

PASSDATA variable

Passes the data in the specified variable to another jBC program, the executing jBC program should retrieve the data using the COLLECTDATA statement.

RTNDATA variable

The RTNDATA statement returns any data passed from an executing jBC program in the specified variable. The executing jBC program should use the RTNDATA statement to pass data back to the calling program.

NOTES

The clauses may be specified in any order within the statement but only one of each clause may exist.

EXAMPLE

   V.CMD = 'COUNT .'
   HUSH ON
   EXECUTE V.CMD RETURNING V.CNT
   HUSH OFF
   CRT V.CNT<1,2>     ;* e.g. 15

EXAMPLE 2

   EXECUTE 'SELECT F.TEMP' :@FM: 'SAVE.LIST TEMP-LIST'

EXAMPLE 3

   EXECUTE CHAR(255) : 'kecho $SHELL'   ;* /usr/bin/ksh

EXAMPLE 4

   EXECUTE 'df -m' CAPTURING V.OUTPUT
   LOOP
      REMOVE V.LINE FROM V.OUTPUT SETTING V.STATUS
      CRT '[' : V.LINE : ']'
      IF V.STATUS EQ 0 THEN BREAK
   REPEAT

Sample output of the last example:

    [Filesystem    MB blocks      Free %Used    Iused %Iused Mounted on]
    [/dev/hd4         512.00    276.03   47%    12020    16% /]
    [/dev/hd2        5120.00   1398.12   73%    67516    18% /usr]
    [/dev/hd9var      640.00     95.71   86%    13280    36% /var]
    [/dev/hd3         768.00    505.89   35%     8812     7% /tmp]
    [/dev/hd1         128.00    121.68    5%      185     1% /home]
    [/proc                 -         -    -         -     -  /proc]

FIELD

The FIELD function returns a multi-character delimited field from within a string.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FIELD(string, delimiter, occurrence{, extractCount})

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

string specifies the string, from which the field(s) is to be extracted.

delimiter specifies the character or characters that delimit the fields within the dynamic array.

occurrence should evaluate to an integer of value 1 or higher. It specifies the delimiter used as the starting point for the extraction.

extractCount is an integer that specifies the number of fields to extract. If omitted, assumes one.

NOTES

If the emulation option, jbase_field, is set then the field delimiter may consist of more than a single character, allowing fields to be delimited by complex codes.

See also: GROUP

EXAMPLES

   V.STRING = 'ABC/DEF/QWE/XYZ'
* One field
   CRT FIELD(V.STRING, '/', 2)         ;* DEF
* Alternate way
   CRT V.STRING['/', 2, 1]             ;* DEF
* More than one field
   CRT FIELD(V.STRING, '/', 2, 2)      ;* DEF/QWE
   CRT V.STRING['/', 2, 3]             ;* DEF/QWE/XYZ
   CRT DQUOTE( FIELD(V.STRING, '/', 2, 99) )    ;* take "all the rest after 1st"

FILELOCK

Use the FILELOCK statement to acquire a lock on an entire file. This prevents other users from updating the file until the program releases it. A FILELOCK statement that does not specify lock.type is equivalent to obtaining an update record lock on every record of the file. An open file is specified by file.variable. If no file.variable is specified, the default file is assumed; if the file is neither accessible nor open, the program enters the debugger.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FILELOCK filevar { LOCKED statements } { ON ERROR statements }

FILEUNLOCK filevar { ON ERROR statements }

DESCRIPTION

When the FILELOCK statement is executed, it will attempt to take an exclusive lock on the entire file. If there are any locks currently outstanding on the file, then the statement will block until there are no more locks on the file. The use of the LOCKED clause allows the application to perform an unblocked operation.

When the FILELOCK statement is blocked waiting for a lock, other processes may continue to perform database operations on that file, including the removal of record locks and the taking of record locks. Once the FILELOCK is taken, it will block ALL database accesses to the file whether or not the access involves record locks. i.e. a READ will block once it has been executed, as will, CLEARFILE etc,. The lock continues until the file is closed, the program terminates, or a FILEUNLOCK statement is executed.

NOTE: The FILELOCK statement might differ to those found on other vendors systems. You should also not that the use of these statements for other than administration work, for example, within batch jobs, is not recommended. The replacement of such with more judicious use of item locks is advised.

IMPLEMENTATION NOTES

The FILELOCK command is implemented using the native locking mechanism of the operating system and is entirely at its mercy. Because of this, you may see some slight implementation differences between operating systems. These comments on native locking do not apply to the NT platform as TAFC uses the NT locking mechanism.

The uses of the native (UNIX) locking mechanism means the file in question MUST NOT use the jBASE locking mechanism. You can set a file to use the native locking mechanism by using the jchmod command:

jchmod +N filename {filename ...}

Alternatively, like this when the file is originally created:

    CREATE-FILE filename 1,1 23,1 NETWORK=TRUE

If the file continues to use the jBASE record locking, then the ON ERROR clause will be taken and the SYSTEM(0) and STATUS functions will set to 22 to indicate the error.

EXAMPLES

OPEN '','SLIPPERS' TO FILEVAR ELSE STOP "CAN'T OPEN FILE"
FILELOCK FILEVAR LOCKED STOP 'FILE IS ALREADY LOCKED'
FILEUNLOCK DATA
OPEN '','SLIPPERS' ELSE STOP "CAN'T OPEN FILE"
FILELOCK LOCKED STOP 'FILE IS ALREADY LOCKED'
PRINT "The file is locked."
FILEUNLOCK

FILEUNLOCK

Use the FILEUNLOCK statement to release a file lock set by the FILELOCK statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FILEUNLOCK [file.variable] [ ON ERROR statements ]

file.variable specifies a file previously locked with a FILELOCK statement. If file.variable is not specified, the default file with the FILELOCK statement is assumed .If file.variable is not a valid file variable then the FILEUNLOCK statement will enter the debugger.

The ON ERROR Clause

The ON ERROR clause is optional in the FILELOCK statement. The ON ERROR clause lets you specify an alternative for program termination when encountering a fatal error during processing of the FILELOCK statement. If a fatal error occurs, with no ON ERROR clause specified, the program enters the debugger.

If the ON ERROR clause is used, the value returned by the STATUS function is the error number.

EXAMPLE

In the following example, the first FILEUNLOCK statement unlocks the default file. The second FILEUNLOCK statement unlocks the file variable FILE.

OPEN '', 'SLIPPERS' ELSE STOP "CAN'T OPEN SLIPPERS"
FILELOCK
FILEUNLOCK
OPEN 'PIPE' TO FILEVAR ELSE STOP
FILELOCK FILEVAR
FILEUNLOCK FILEVAR

FIND

The FIND statement determines if a specified string fully matches to an element in a dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FIND expression1 IN Var1 {, expression2} SETTING Var2 {, Var3 {, Var4}} \
     THEN | ELSE statement(s)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 evaluates to the string with which to compare every element of the dynamic array. Var1 is the dynamic array that will be searched. The FIND command will normally find the first occurrence of expression1 unless expression2 is specified. If specified then expression2 will cause a specific occurrence of expression1 to be located. The three variables Var2, Var3, Var4 are used to record the Field, Value and Sub-Value positions in which expression1 was found.

If expression1 is found in any element of Var1 then Vars 2, 3 and 4 are set to the position in which it was found and any THEN clause of the statement is executed. If expression1 is not found within any element of the dynamic array then Vars 2, 3 and 4 are undefined and the ELSE clause of the statement is executed.

NOTES

The statement may omit either the THEN clause or the ELSE clause but may not omit both. It is valid for the statement to contain both clauses if required.

See also: LOCATE, FINDSTR

EXAMPLE

   V.ARRAY = 'ABC'   \
       :@FM: 'DEF' :@VM: '123' :@VM: 'XYZ' :@VM: '456' \
       :@FM: '789' \
       :@FM: '---' : @SM: 'XYZ'
   GOSUB RESET.IT
   FIND 'XYZ' IN V.ARRAY SETTING V.FLD, V.VAL ELSE NULL
   CRT V.FLD, V.VAL            ;*   2       3
   GOSUB RESET.IT
   FIND 'XYYYZ' IN V.ARRAY SETTING V.FLD, V.VAL ELSE NULL
   CRT V.FLD, V.VAL            ;*   0       0
   GOSUB RESET.IT
   FIND 'XYZ' IN V.ARRAY, 2 SETTING V.FLD, V.VAL, V.SVAL ELSE NULL
   CRT V.FLD, V.VAL, V.SVAL    ;*   4       1       2
   GOSUB RESET.IT
* Full match is required
   FIND 'XY' IN V.ARRAY SETTING V.FLD, V.VAL ELSE NULL
   CRT V.FLD, V.VAL            ;*   0       0
   GOSUB RESET.IT
   STOP
RESET.IT:
   V.FLD = 0  ; V.VAL = 0  ;  V.SVAL = 0
   RETURN

FINDSTR

The FINDSTR statement locates a string as a substring of a dynamic array element. It is similar in operation to the FIND statement, except that the full match isn't required.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FINDSTR expression1 IN Var1 {, expression2} SETTING Var2 {,Var3 {, Var4}} \
        THEN | ELSE statement(s)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 evaluates to the string with which to search every element of the dynamic array. Var1 is the actual dynamic array that will be searched. FINDSTR will normally locate the first occurrence of expression1 unless expression2 is specified. If specified then expression2 will cause a specific occurrence of expression1 to be located. The three variables Var2, Var3, Var4 are used to record the Field, Value and Sub-Value positions in which expression1 was found.

If expression1 is found as a substring of any element of Var1 then Vars 2, 3 and 4 are set to the position in which it was found and the THEN clause of the statement is executed if it is present. If expression1 is not found within any element of the dynamic array then Vars 2,3 and 4 are undefined and the ELSE clause of the statement is executed.

NOTES

The statement may omit either the THEN clause or the ELSE clause but may not omit both. It is valid for the statement to contain both clauses if required.

EXAMPLE

   V.ARRAY = 'ABC'   \
         :@FM: 'DEF' :@VM: '123' :@VM: 'XYZ' :@VM: '456' \
         :@FM: '789' \
         :@FM: '---' : @SM: 'XYZ'
   V.FLD = 0  ; V.VAL = 0  ;  V.SVAL = 0
   FINDSTR 'XY' IN V.ARRAY SETTING V.FLD, V.VAL ELSE NULL
   CRT V.FLD, V.VAL            ;*   2       3

FOLD

The FOLD function re-delimits a string by replacing spaces with attribute marks at positions defined by a length parameter.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FOLD(expression1, expression2)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 evaluates a string to be re-delimited.

expression2 evaluates to a positive integer that represents the maximum number of characters between delimiters in the resultant string.

NOTES

The FOLD function creates a number of sub-strings such that the length of each sub-string does not exceed the length value in expression2. It converts spaces to attribute marks except when enclosed in sub-strings and removes extraneous spaces.

EXAMPLES

The following examples show how the FOLD function delimits text based on the length parameter. The underscores represent attribute marks.

q = "Smoking is one of the leading causes of statistics"
CRT OCONV( FOLD(q, 7), 'MCP' )

Output:

    Smoking^is one^of the^leading^causes^of^statist^ics

q = "Hello world"
CRT OCONV( FOLD(q, 5), 'MCP' )

Output:

    Hello^world

q = "Let this be a reminder to you all" \
    : " that this organization will not tolerate failure."
CRT OCONV( FOLD(q, 30), 'MCP')

Output:

Let this be a reminder to you^all that this organization^will not tolerate failure.

q = "the end"
CRT OCONV( FOLD(q, 0), 'MCP' )

Output:

    t^h^e^e^n^d

FOOTING

The FOOTING statement halts all subsequent output to the terminal at the end of each output page. The statement allows the evaluation and display of an expression at the foot of each page. Output, which is current, and being sent to the terminal, the output is paused until the entry of a carriage return at the terminal (unless the N option is specified either in the current HEADING or in this FOOTING).

COMMAND SYNTAX

FOOTING expression

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The expression should evaluate to a string, which is printed at the bottom of every page of output. The string could contain a number of interpreted special characters, replaced in the string before printing.

The following characters have special meaning within the string:

Value | Description
"C{n}" | Center the line. If n is specified the output line is
| assumed to be n characters long.
"D" or \ | Replace with the current date.
"L" or ] | Replace with the newline sequence.
"N" | Terminal output does not pause at the end of each
| page.
"P" or ^ | Replace with the current page number.
"PP" or ^^ | Replace with the current page number in a field of 4
| characters. The field is right justified.
"T" or   | Replace with the current time and date.
" | Replace with a single " character.

NOTES

If the output is to the printer a PRINTER ON statement is in force; output sent to the terminal with the CRT statement is not paged; if output is to the terminal then all output is paged.

EXAMPLE

FOOTING 'Programming staff by weight Page "P"'

FOR

The FOR statement allows the construction of looping constructs within the program, which is controlled by a counting variable; this can be terminated early by expressions tested after every iteration.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FOR var=expression1 TO expression2 { STEP expression3 }  \
   { WHILE | UNTIL expression4 }
...
NEXT {var}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

var is the counting variable used to control the loop. The first time the loop is entered var is assigned the value of expression1, which must evaluate to a numeric value. After each iteration of the loop, var is automatically incremented by one.

expression2 must also evaluate to a numeric value as it causes the loop to terminate when the value of var is greater than the value of this expression. expression2 is evaluated at the start of every iteration of the loop and compared with the value of expression1.

If the STEP expression3 clause is included within the statement, var will automatically be incremented by the value of expression3 after each iteration of the loop. expression3 is evaluated at the start of each iteration.

expression3 may be negative, in which case the loop will terminate when var is less than expression2. The statement may optionally include either an evaluated WHILE or UNTIL clause (not both), before each iteration of the loop. When the WHILE clause is specified the loop will only continue with the next iteration if expression4 evaluates to Boolean TRUE. When the UNTIL clause is specified the loop will only continue with the next iteration if expression4 evaluates to Boolean FALSE.

NOTES

Because expression2 and expression3 must be evaluated upon each iteration of the loop, you should only code complex expressions here if they may change within each iteration. If the values they yield will not change then you should assign the value of these expressions to a variable before coding the loop statement. You can replace expressions 3 and 4 with these variables. This can offer large performance increases where complex expressions are in use.

See also: BREAK, CONTINUE.

EXAMPLE

   V.ARRAY = ''
   FOR V.I = 1 TO 10
      V.ARRAY<-1> = 'Element #' : V.I
   NEXT V.I
   CRT V.ARRAY<6>                          ;* Element #6
   //
   FOR V.I = 10 TO 1 STEP -2 WHILE V.I GT 3
      DEL V.ARRAY<V.I>
   NEXT V.I
   CRT V.ARRAY<6>                          ;* Element #9
   CRT V.ARRAY<3>                          ;* Element #3

FUNCTION

Identifies a user-defined function, which can be invoked by other jBC programs, arguments to the function can optionally be declared.

COMMAND SYNTAX

FUNCTION name({ MAT } variable, { MAT } variable...)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Name is the name by which the function is invoked.

Variable is an expression used to pass values between the calling program and the function.

NOTES

Use the FUNCTION statement to identify user-written source code functions. Each function must be coded in separate records and the record Id must match that of the Function Name, which in turn should match the reference in the calling program.

The optional comma separated variable list can be a number of expressions that pass values between the calling programs and the function. To pass an array the variable name must be preceded by the MAT keyword. When a user-written function is called, the calling program must specify the same number of variables that are specified in the FUNCTION statement.

An extra 'hidden' variable is used to return a value from the user-written function. The value to be returned can be specified within the Function by the RETURN (value) statement. If using the RETURN statement without a value then by default it returns an empty string.

The calling program must specify a DEFFUN or DEFB statement to describe the function to be called and the function source must be cataloged and locatable similar to subroutines.

EXAMPLE

The function:

    FUNCTION ADD.FUNC(operand1, operand2)
    result = operand1 + operand2
    RETURN(result)
END

The calling program:

   DEFFUN ADD.FUNC()
   CRT ADD.FUNC(1, 2)           ;* 3
   CRT ADD.FUNC(100, 200)       ;* 300

GET

The GET statement reads a block of data directly from a device.

COMMAND SYNTAX

GET Var {,length} { SETTING Count } FROM Device { UNTIL TermChars } \
    { RETURNING TermChar }  { WAITING Timeout } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Var is the variable in which to place the input (from the previously open Device).

If length is specified, it limits the number of characters read from the input device.

If the optional Count option is used, it returns the number of characters actually read from the device.

Device is the file variable associated with the result from a successful OPENSEQ or OPENSER command.

TermChars specifies one or more characters that will terminate input.

TermChar The actual character that terminated input

Timeout is the number of seconds to wait for input. If no input is present when the timeout period expires, the ELSE clause (if specified) is executed.

NOTES

The GET statement does no pre-or post-processing of the input data stream - nor does it handle any terminal echo characteristics. If this is desired, the application - or device drive - will handle it. If there are no specified length and timeout expressions, the default input length is one (1) character. If no length is specified, but TermChars are, there is no limit to the number of characters input. The GET syntax requires a specified THEN or ELSE clause, or both. The THEN clause executes when the data received is error free; the ELSE clause executes when the data is unreceiveable (or a timeout occurs).

See: GETX

HEADING

Heading halts all subsequent output to the terminal at the end of each page. The statement evaluates and displays an expression at the top of each page. Current output sent to the terminal, is paused until entry of a carriage return at the terminal - unless the N option is specified.

COMMAND SYNTAX

HEADING expression

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The expression should evaluate to a string printed at the top of every page of output. The string may contain a number of interpreted special characters, replaced in the string before printing. The following characters have special meaning within the string:

Value | Description
"C{n}" | Center the line. If n is specified the output line is
| assumed to be n characters long.
"D" or \ | Replace with the current date.
"L" or ] | Replace with the newline sequence.
"N" | Terminal output does not pause at the end of each
| page.
"P" or ^ | Replace with the current page number.
"PP" or ^^ | Replace with the current page number in a field of 4
| characters. The field is right justified.
"T" or   | Replace with the current time and date.
" | Replace with a single " character.

NOTES

If output is to the printer, a PRINTER ON statement is in use, and does not page output sent to the terminal with the CRT statement. Unless you specify the "N" option, all output sent to the terminal is paged.

EXAMPLES

HEADING 'Programming staff by size of waist Page "P"'

ICONVS

Use ICONVS to convert each element of dynamic.array to a specified internal storage format.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ICONVS(dynamic.array, conversion)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

conversion is an expression that evaluates to one or more valid conversion codes, separated by value marks (ASCII 253).

Each element of dynamic.array is converted to the internal format specified by conversion and is returned in a dynamic array. If multiple codes are used, they are applied from left to right. The first conversion code converts the value of each element of dynamic.array. The second conversion code converts the value of each element of the output of the first conversion, and so on. If dynamic.array evaluates to null, it returns null. If an element of dynamic.array is null, null it returns null for that element. If conversion evaluates to null, the ICONV function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

The STATUS function reflects the result of the conversion:

Code | Description
0 | The conversion is successful.
1 | An element of dynamic.array is invalid. It returns an empty string,
| unless dynamic.array is null, in which case it returns null.
2 | Conversion is invalid.
3 | Successful conversion of possibly invalid data.

See also: OCONVS function.

IN

The IN statement allows the program to receive raw data from the input device, which is normally the terminal keyboard, one character at a time.

COMMAND SYNTAX

IN Var { FOR expression THEN | ELSE statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Var will be assigned the numeric value (0 - 255 decimal) of the next character received from the input device. The statement will normally wait indefinitely (block) for a character from the keyboard.

Specifying the FOR clause to the IN statement allows the statement to stop waiting for keyboard after a specified amount of time. The expression should evaluate to a numeric value, which will be taken as the number of deci-seconds (tenths of a second) to wait before abandoning the input.

The FOR clause must have either or both of the THEN or ELSE clauses If a character is received from the input device before the time-out period then Var is assigned its numeric value and the THEN clause is executed (if present). If the input statement times out before a character is received then Var is unaltered and the ELSE clause is executed (if present).

NOTES

See also: INPUT, INPUTNULL.

EXAMPLE

   LOOP
      IN in_key
      IF in_key EQ 27 THEN ;* ESC seen
         IN in_key_2 FOR 2 THEN ;* Function Key?
            IN in_key_3 FOR 2 THEN
               CRT ''
               BEGIN CASE
               CASE in_key_2 EQ 79 AND in_key_3 EQ 80
                  CRT 'F1 detected'
               CASE in_key_2 EQ 79 AND in_key_3 EQ 81
                  CRT 'F2 detected'
               END CASE
            END
         END ELSE
            CRT ''
            CRT 'ESC pressed, exiting'
            STOP
         END
      END
   REPEAT

INPUT

The INPUT statement allows the program to collect data from the current input device, which will normally be the terminal keyboard but may be stacked input from the same or separate program.

COMMAND SYNTAX

INPUT {@ (expression1 {, expression2 )}{:} Var{{, expression3}, expression4} \
      {:}{_} { WITH expression5 } { FOR expression6 THEN | ELSE statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

@(expression1, expression2) allows the screen cursor to be positioned to the specified column and row before the input prompt is sent to the screen. The syntax for this is the same as the @( ) function described earlier.

Var is the variable in which the input data is to be stored.

expression3, when specified, should evaluate to a numeric value. This will cause input to be terminated with an automatic newline sequence after exactly this number of characters has been input. If the _ option is specified with expression4 then the automatic newline sequence is not specified but any subsequent input characters are belled to the terminal and thrown away.

expression4 when specified, should evaluate to a sequence of 1 to 3 characters. The first character will be printed expression3 times to define the field on the terminal screen. At the end of the input if less than expression3 characters were input then the rest of the field is padded with the second character if it was supplied. If the third character is supplied then the cursor will be positioned after the last character input rather than at the end of the input field.

The : option, when specified, suppress the echoing of the newline sequence to the terminal. This will leave the cursor positioned after the last input character on the terminal screen.

WITH expression5 allows the default input delimiter (the newline sequence) to be changed. When specified, expression5, should evaluate to a string of up to 256 characters, each of which may delimit the input field. If this clause is used then the newline sequence is removed as a delimiter and must be specified explicitly within expression5 as CHAR(10).

The "FOR" clause allows the "INPUT" statement to time out after a specified waiting period instead of blocking as normal Expression6 should evaluate to a numeric value, which will be taken as the number of deci-seconds (tenths of a second) to wait before timing out. The time-out value is used as the time between each keystroke and should a time-out occur, Var would hold the characters that were input until the time-out.

The FOR clause requires either the THEN and ELSE clauses or both; if no time-out occurs the THEN clause is taken. If a time-out does occur, the ELSE clause is taken.

NOTES

The INPUT statement will always examine the data input stack before requesting data from the input device. If data is present on the stack then it is used to satisfy INPUT statements one field at a time until the stack is exhausted. Once exhausted, the INPUT statement will revert to the input device for further input. There is no way (by default) to input a null field to the INPUT@ statement. If the INPUT@ statement receives the newline sequence only as input, then the Var will be unchanged. Use the INPUTNULL statement to define a character that indicates a NULL input.

Use the CONTROL-CHARS command to control whether or not control characters (i.e. those outside the range x'1F' - x'7F') are accepted by INPUT.

See also: IN, INPUTNULL.

EXAMPLE

Ask user for an input; time limit is 60 seconds; every 3 seconds the remaining time is updated on user screen.

   V.TIMEOUT = 60
   GOSUB UPD.CNT
   V.ANS = ''
   LOOP
   WHILE V.ANS EQ '' DO
      INPUT V.ANS, 1 : FOR 30 ELSE
         V.TIMEOUT -= 3
         IF V.TIMEOUT LE 0 THEN BREAK
         GOSUB UPD.CNT
      END
   REPEAT
   IF V.ANS NE '' THEN CRT 'The choice was', DQUOTE(V.ANS)
   ELSE CRT "The choice wasn't done"
   STOP
UPD.CNT:
   CRT @(0):'Seconds left: ': FMT(V.TIMEOUT, '2R') : '. Your choice':
   RETURN

EXAMPLE 2

Pad the input field.

Code:

   CRT @(-1)
   INPUT @(17,2):the_input,50,'_..':_

User screen:

                    ? _________________________________________________

See also: PROMPT.

IOCTL

The jBC language provides an intrinsic function called IOCTL that behaves in a similar manner to the C function ioctl(). Its purpose is to allow commands to be sent to the database driver for a particular file, and then to receive a reply from the database driver.

As with the C function ioctl, the use of IOCTL is highly dependent upon the database driver it is talking to. Each database driver may choose to provide certain common functionality, or may add its own commands and so on. This is especially true of user-written database drivers.

First, an example of a source program that opens a file and finds the type of file:

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "MD" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "MD"
status = ""
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_FILESTATUS, status) THEN
   PRINT "Type of file = " : DQUOTE(status<1>)
END ELSE
   PRINT "IOCTL FAILED !! unknown file type"
END

If the ELSE clause is taken, it does not necessarily mean there is an error, it only means that the database driver for file "MD" does not support the command that was requested from it. The file JBC.h is supplied with jBASE in the directory TAFC_HOME sub directory include. If the source is compiled with the jbc or BASIC command, this directory is automatically included in the search path and no special action is needed by the programmer for the "INCLUDE JBC.h" statement.

The format of the IOCTL function is:

IOCTL(Filevar, Command, Parameter)

Where:

filevar Is a variable that has had a file opened against it using the OPEN statement. However, if you want to use the default file variable, use -1 in this position.

For example:

OPEN "MD" ELSE STOP
filevar = -1
IF IOCTL(filevar, JIOCTL_COMMAND_xxx, status)
...

command can be any numeric value (or variable containing a numeric). However, it is up to the database driver to support that particular command number. The remainder of this chapter describes the common IOCTL command numbers supported by the jBASE database drivers provided.

Status Pass here a jBC variable. The use of this variable depends upon the command parameter, and will be described later for each command supported.

The return value is 0 for failure, or 1 for success. A value of "-1" generally shows the command has not been recognized.

The remainder of this section will deal with the IOCTL commands that are supported by the provided jBASE database drivers, and the JBC_COMMAND_GETFILENAME command that is supported for all database drivers.

JBC_COMMAND_GETFILENAME COMMAND Using this command to the IOCTL function, you can determine the exact file name that was used to open the file. This is helpful because jEDI uses Q pointers, F pointers and the JEDIFILEPATH environment variable to actually open the file, and the application can never be totally sure where the resultant file was really opened. Normally of course, this is of no concern to the application.

EXAMPLE

Open the file CUSTOMERS and find out the exact path that was used to open the file.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "CUSTOMERS" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "CUSTOMERS"
filename = ""
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JBC_COMMAND_GETFILENAME, filename) ELSE
   CRT "IOCTL failed !!" ; EXIT(2)
END
PRINT "Full file path = " : DQUOTE(filename)

This command is executed by the jBC library code rather than the jEDI library code or the database drivers, so it can be run against a file descriptor for any file type.

JIOCTL_COMMAND_CONVERT COMMAND

Some of the jBC database drivers will perform an automatic conversion of the input and output record when performing reads and writes.

An example of this is when writing to a directory. In this case, the attribute marks will be converted to new-line characters and a trailing new-line character added. Similarly for reading from a directory the new-line characters will be replaced with attribute marks, and the trailing new-line character will be deleted.

The above example is what happens for the database driver for directories. It assumes by default that the record being read or written is a text file and that the conversion is necessary. It tries to apply some intelligence to reading files, as text files always have a trailing new-line character. Therefore, if a file is read without a trailing new-line character, the database driver assumes the file must be a binary file rather than a text file, and no conversion takes place.

This conversion of data works in most cases and usually requires no special intervention from the programmer.

There are cases however, when this conversion needs to be controlled and interrogated, and the IOCTL function call with the JIOCTL_COMMAND_CONVERT command provides the jBASE database drivers that support this conversion with commands to control it.

The call to IOCTL, if successful, will only affect file operations that use the same file descriptor. Consider the following code:

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "MD" TO FILEVAR1 ELSE ...
OPEN "MD" TO FILEVAR2 ELSE ...
IF IOCTL(FILEVAR1, JIOCTL_COMMAND_CONVERT, 'RB')

In the above example, any future file operations using variable FILEVAR1 will be controlled by the change forced in the IOCTL request. Any file operations using variable FILEVAR2 will not be affected and will use the default file operation.

Input to the IOCTL is a string of controls delimited by a comma that tell the database driver what to do. The output from the IOCTL can optionally be a string to show the last conversion that the driver performed on the file.

The descriptions of the available controls that can be passed as input to this IOCTL function are:

Code | Description
RB | All future reads to be in binary (no conversion)
RT | All future reads to be in text format (always do a
| conversion)
RS | Return to caller the status of the last read("B" = binary,
| "T" = text)
WB | All future writes to be in binary (no conversion)
WT | All future writes to be in text format (always do a
| conversion)
WI | All future writes to decide themselves whether binary or text
WS | Return to caller the status of the last write ("B" = binary,
| "T" = text )
KB | All future reads/writes have the record key unaltered
KT | All future reads/writes have the record key modified
KI | All future reads/writes to decide if to do a conversion
KS | Return to caller the status of the last record key
| ("B" = binary, "T" = text )

EXAMPLE 1

The application wants to open a file, and to ensure that all reads and writes to that file are in binary, and that no translation such as new-lines to attribute marks is performed.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "FILE" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "FILE"
IF IOCTL(DSCB,JIOCTL_COMMAND_CONVERT, 'RB,WB') ELSE
   CRT "UNABLE TO IOCTL FILE 'FILE'" ; EXIT(2)
END

EXAMPLE 2

Read a record from a file, and find out if the last record read was in text format (were new-lines converted to attribute marks and the trailing new-line deleted), or in binary format (with no conversion at all).

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "." TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "."
READ rec FROM DSCB, "prog.o" ELSE STOP 202, "prog.o"
status = "RS"
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_CONVERT, status) THEN
   IF status EQ "T" THEN CRT "TEXT" ELSE CRT "BINARY"
END ELSE
   CRT "The IOCTL failed !!"
END

JIOCTL_COMMAND_FILESTATUS COMMAND

The JIOCTL_COMMAND_FILESTATUS command will return an attribute delimited list of the status of the file to the caller.

Attribute | Description
<1> | File type, as a string
<2> | File type, as a string
<2> | FileFlags, as decimal number, show LOG, BACKUP and TRANS
<3> | BucketQty, as decimal number, number of buckets in the file
<4> | BucketSize, as decimal number, size of each bucket in bytes
<5> | SecSize, as decimal number, size of secondary data space
<6> | Restore Spec, a string showing any restore re-size
| specification
<7> | Locking identifiers, separated by multi-values
<8> | FileFlags showing LOG, BACKUP and TRANSACTION permissions
<8,1> | Set to non-zero to suppress logging on this file
<8,2> | Set to non-zero to suppress transaction boundaries on this
| file
<8,3> | Set to no-zero to suppress backup of the file using jbackup
<9> | Hashing algorithm used

EXAMPLE 1

Open a file and see if the file type is a directory.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN ".." TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, ".."
status = ""
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_FILESTATUS, status) ELSE
   CRT "IOCTL failed !!" ; EXIT(2)
END
IF status<1> EQ "UD" THEN
   PRINT "File is a directory"
END ELSE
   PRINT "File type is " : DQUOTE(status<1>)
   PRINT "This is not expected for .."
END

EXAMPLE 2

Open a file ready to perform file operations in a transaction against it. Make sure the file has not been removed as a transaction type file by a previous invocation of the command "jchmod -T CUSTOMERS".

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "CUSTOMERS" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "CUSTOMERS"
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_FILESTATUS, status) ELSE
   CRT "IOCTL failed !!" ; EXIT(2)
END
IF status<8,2> THEN
   CRT "Error ! File CUSTOMERS is not"
   CRT "part of transaction boundaries !!"
   CRT 'Use "jchmod +T CUSTOMERS" !!'
   EXIT(2)
END

JIOCTL_COMMAND_FINDRECORD COMMAND

This command will find out if a record exists on a file without the need to actually read in the record. This can provide large performance gains in certain circumstances.

EXAMPLE

Before writing out a control record, make sure it doesn't already exist. As the control record is quite large, it will provide performance gains to simply test if the output record already exists, rather than reading it in using the READ statement to see if it exists.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "outputfile" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "outputfile"
* Make up the output record to write out in "output"
key = "output.out"
rc = IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_FINDRECORD, key)
BEGIN CASE
   CASE rc EQ 0
      WRITE output ON DSCB,key
      CRT "Data written to key " : key
   CASE rc GT 0
      CRT "No further action, record already exists"
   CASE 1
      CRT "IOCTL not supported for file type"
END CASE

JIOCTL_COMMAND_FINDRECORD_EXTENDED COMMAND

This command to the IOCTL function returns the record size and the time and date the record was last updated. If the record does not exist, null is returned. The time/date stamp is returned in UTC format.

EXAMPLE

Print the time and data of last update for each record in filename.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "filename" TO DSCB ELSE STOP 201, "filename"
*
* Select each record in the newly opened file
*
SELECT DSCB
LOOP WHILE READNEXT record.key DO
*
* Get the details on the record and look for errors.
*
   record.info = record.key
   IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_FINDRECORD_EXTENDED, record.info) ELSE
      CRT "Error! File driver does not support this"
      STOP
   END
*
* Extract and convert the returned data
*
   record.size = record.info<1>
   record.utc = record.info<2>
   record.time = OCONV(record.utc, 'U0ff0')
   record.date = OCONV(record.utc, 'U0ff1')
*
* Print the information.
*
   PRINT "Record key " :record.key: " last updated at " :
   PRINT OCONV(record.time, 'MTS'): " " :
   PRINT OCONV(record.date, 'D4')
REPEAT

JIOCTL_COMMAND_HASH_RECORD COMMAND

For jBASE hashed files such as j3 and j4 each record is pseudo-randomly written to one of the buckets (or groups) of the hashed file. The actual bucket it is written to depends upon two factors:

The actual record key (or item-id)

The number of buckets in the file (or modulo)

This IOCTL command shows which bucket number the record would be found in, given the input record key. The bucket number is in the range 0 to (b-1) where b is the number of buckets in the file specified when the file was created (probably using CREATE-FILE).

The command only returns the expected bucket number, as is no indication that the record actually exists in the file.

Two attributes are returned by this command. The first is the hash value that the record key has hashed to, and the second attribute is the bucket number.

EXAMPLE

Open a file, and find out what bucket number the record "PIPE&SLIPPER" would be found in.

INCLUDE JBC.h
OPEN "WEDDING-PRESENTS" TO DSCB ELSE STOP
key = "PIPE&SLIPPER"
parm = key
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_HASH_RECORD, parm) THEN
  PRINT "key " :key: " would be in bucket " :parm<2>
END ELSE
   CRT "IOCTL failed, command not supported"
END

JIOCTL_COMMAND_HASH_LOCK COMMAND

The jEDI locking mechanism for records in jEDI provided database drivers is not strictly a 100% record locking mechanism. Instead, it uses the hashed value of the record key to give a value from 0 to 230-1 to describe the record key. The IOCTL command can be used to determine how a record key would be converted into a hashed value for use by the locking mechanism.

EXAMPLE

Lock a record in a file and find out what the lock id of the record key is. The example then calls the jRLA locking demon and the display of locks taken should include the lock taken by this program.

INCLUDE JBC.h
DEFC getpid()
OPEN "WEDDING-PRESENTS" TO DSCB ELSE STOP
key = "PIPE&SLIPPER"
parm = key
IF IOCTL(DSCB, JIOCTL_COMMAND_HASH_LOCK, parm) ELSE
   CRT "IOCTL failed, command not supported"
   EXIT(2)
END
PRINT "The lock ID for the key is " : parm
PRINT "Our process id is " : getpid()

ITYPE

ITYPE function is used to return the value resulting from the evaluation of an I-type expression in a jBASE file dictionary.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ITYPE(i.type)

I.type is an expression evaluating to the contents of the compiled I-descriptor. You must compile the I-descriptor before the ITYPE function uses it; otherwise, you get a run-time error message.

Using several methods set the I.type to the evaluated I-descriptor in several ways. One way is to read the I-descriptor from a file dictionary into a variable, then use the variable as the argument to the ITYPE function. If the I-descriptor references a record ID, the current value of the system variable @ID is used. If the I-descriptor, references field values in a data record, the data is taken from the current value of the system variable @RECORD.

To assign field values to @RECORD, read a record from the data file into @RECORD before invoking the ITYPE function.

If i.type evaluates to null, the ITYPE function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

NOTE: Set the @FILENAME to the name of the file before ITYPE execution.

EXAMPLE

* Data preparation
*
   V.FILE = 'F.TEMP'
   EXECUTE 'DELETE-FILE ' : V.FILE
   EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE ' : V.FILE : ' 1 101 TYPE=J4'
   OPEN V.FILE TO F.TEMP ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP'
   OPEN 'DICT', V.FILE TO F.TEMP.DICT ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP]D'
* Field 1 dictionary entry
   R.DICT.D1 = ''
   R.DICT.D1<1> = 'D'
   R.DICT.D1<2> = '1'
   R.DICT.D1<5> = '25L'
   R.DICT.D1<6> = 'S'
   WRITE R.DICT.D1 TO F.TEMP.DICT, 'FOOTWEAR'
*
* I-descriptor
   V.DESCR = 'SIZE'
   R.DICT.I = ''
   R.DICT.I<1> = 'I'
   R.DICT.I<2> = 'FOOTWEAR[":", 2, 1]'
   R.DICT.I<4> = V.DESCR
   R.DICT.I<5> = '3R'
   R.DICT.I<6> = 'S'
   WRITE R.DICT.I TO F.TEMP.DICT, V.DESCR
*
* Data records
   R.DATA = ''
   R.DATA<1> = 'SLIPPERS:8'
   WRITE R.DATA TO F.TEMP, 'JIM'
   R.DATA = ''
   R.DATA<1> = 'BOOTS:10'
   WRITE R.DATA TO F.TEMP, 'GREG'
   R.DATA = ''
   R.DATA<1> = 'SLIPPERS:5'
   WRITE R.DATA TO F.TEMP, 'ALAN'
*
* Data is prepared; now proceed it
*
   @FILENAME = V.FILE
   READ V.ITYPE FROM F.TEMP.DICT, V.DESCR ELSE ABORT
*
   SSELECT F.TEMP TO V.PEOPLE.L
   LOOP
      READNEXT V.ID FROM V.PEOPLE.L ELSE BREAK
      @ID = V.ID
      READ @RECORD FROM F.TEMP, @ID ELSE ABORT
      V.RET = ITYPE(V.ITYPE)
      CRT @ID : "'S FOOTWEAR HAS SIZE " : V.RET
   REPEAT

The output of this program is:

    ALAN'S FOOTWEAR HAS SIZE 5
    GREG'S FOOTWEAR HAS SIZE 10
    JIM'S FOOTWEAR HAS SIZE 8

JQLCOMPILE

JQLCOMPILE compiles a jQL statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

JQLCOMPILE(Statement, Command, Options, Messages)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Statement is the variable, which receives the compiled statement. Majority of functions use the compiled statement to execute and work on the result set etc.

Command is the actual jQL query that you want to compile (such as SELECT or something similar). Use RETRIEVE to obtain data records as the verb rather than an existing jQL verb. This will ensure that the right options are set internally. In addition, use any word that is not a jQL reserved word as the verb and it will work in the same way as RETRIEVE: implement a PLOT command that passes the entire command line into JQLCOMPILE and the results will be the same as if the first word was replaced with RETRIEVE.

Option: You must specify JQLOPT_USE_SELECT to supply a select list to the JQLEXECUTE function; the compile builds a different execution plan if using select lists.

Messages: If the statement fails to compile, this dynamic array is in the STOP format, therefore STOP messages can be programmed and printed. Provides a history of compilation for troubleshooting purposes; Returns -1 if there is a problem found in the statement and 0 for no problem.

JQLFETCH

JQLFETCH is used to fetch the next result in a compiled jQL statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

JQLFETCH(Statement, ControlVar, DataVar)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Statement is the result of a valid call to JQLCOMPILE(), followed by a valid call to JQLEXECUTE().

ControlVar will receive the 'control break' elements of any query. For example, if there are BREAK values in the statement, described here is the the format of ControlVar is:

    Attr 1  Level: 0 means detail line 1 - 25 for the control breaks, the same as the
            A correlative NB.
    Attr 2  Item ID
    Attr 3  Break control Value is 1 if a blank line should be output first.
    Attr 4  Pre-break value for 'B' option in header
    Attr 5  Post-break value for 'B' option in header

DataVar will receive the actual screen data on a LIST statement for instance. The format is one attribute per column.

Applies Attribute 7 Conversions (or attribute 3 in Prime-style DICTS) to the data.

If the property STMT_PROPERTY_FORMAT is set then each attribute is also formatted according to the width and justification of the attribute definition and any override caused by the use of FMT, of DISPLAY. LIKE on the command line.

NOTES

Column headers may also affect the formatting for that column. This function is called until there is no more output (multiple).

JQLPUTPROPERTY

JQLPUTPROPERTY sets a property in a compiled jQL statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

JQLPUTPROPERTY(PropertyValue, Statement, Column, PropertyName)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

PropertyValue specifies the value to be set for the specified property, such as one or "BLAH".

Statement is the result of a valid JQLCOMPILE() function.

Column holds 0 for a general property of the statement, or a column number if the property is set for a specific column.

PropertyName are EQUATED values defined by INCLUDEing the file JQLINTERFACE.h. There are lots of these and someone is going to have to document each one.

This function returns -1 if it locates a problem in the statement and 0 for no problem.

NOTES

Some properties may require JQLEXECUTE()first.

Properties are valid after the compile; this is the main reason for separating the compile and execute into two functions. After compiling, it is possible to examine the properties and set properties before executing.

Sample program illustrating the usage of compiled jQL statement:

INCLUDE jQLProperties.h
   //
   IF NOT( GETENV('TAFC_HOME', V.HOME) ) THEN
      CRT 'TAFC_HOME not defined'
      STOP
   END
   //
   V.QUERY = 'LIST ONLY ' : V.HOME : '/jbcmessages'
   V.STMT = ''
   //
   V.DUMMY = JQLCOMPILE(V.STMT, V.QUERY, 0, V.MSG)
   //
   V.SEL.VAR = ''
   V.RET = JQLEXECUTE(V.STMT, V.SEL.VAR)
   IF V.RET NE 0 THEN CRT 'JQLEXECUTE RETURNED', V.RET  ; STOP
   //
   LOOP
      GOSUB FETCH.NEXT
   UNTIL V.FETCH NE 1
   REPEAT
   //
   STOP
   //
FETCH.NEXT:
   //
   V.FETCH = JQLFETCH(V.STMT, V.CTRL, V.DATA)
   IF V.FETCH NE 1 THEN RETURN
   V.RET = JQLGETPROPERTY(PropertyValue, V.STMT, 0, \
     STMT_PROPERTY_EXECUTE_COUNT)
   CRT 'ID #' : PropertyValue : ':' , V.DATA<1>
   //
   RETURN
END

Output:

    @ID #1: INV_FILE_TYPE
    @ID #2: DEVICE_QUIT
    @ID #3: RTN_NOGOSUB
    @ID #4: ARRAY_ILLEGAL_SIZE
    @ID #5: DIFF_COMMON
    @ID #6: QLNOVERB
    @ID #7: QLPARAMERR
    ...
    @ID #487:   417
    @ID #488:   80044228
    @ID #489:   80044233
    @ID #490:   80045024

LENS

LENS function is used to return a dynamic array of the number of bytes in each element of the dynamic.array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

LENS(dynamic.array)

Each element of dynamic.array must be a string value. The characters in each element of dynamic.array are counted, with the counts returned.

The LENS function includes all blank spaces, including trailing blanks, in the calculation.

If dynamic.array evaluates to a null string, it returns zero (0). If any element of dynamic.array is null, returns zero (0) for that element.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

The LENS function will return the number of characters in the specified expression rather than the number of bytes, in International Mode. If the expression consists of entirely of UTF-8 characters in the ASCII range 0 - 127 then the character length of the expression will equate to the byte length. However, when the expression contains characters outside the ASCII range 0 - 127 then byte length and character length will differ. See BYTELEN function for more information.

NOTES

Do not use programs to manipulate byte counts in International Mode.

LOCATE

LOCATE statement finds the position of an element within a specified dimension of a dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

LOCATE expression1 IN expression2{<expression3{,expression4}>},{, expression5} \
       { BY expression6 } SETTING Var THEN | ELSE statement(s)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 evaluates to the string that will be searched in expression2.

expression2 evaluates to the dynamic array within which expression1 will search for the string.

expression3 and expression4 cause a value or subvalue search respectively, when specified.

expression5 indicates the field, value or subvalue from which the search will begin.

expression6 causes different searches to arrange the elements in different order, which can considerably improve the performance of some searches. The available string values for expression6 are:

String | Description
AL | Values are in ascending alphanumeric order
AR | Values are in right justified, then ascending order
AN | Values are in ascending numeric order
DL | Values are in descending alphanumeric order
DR | Values are in right justified, then descending order
DN | Values are in descending numeric order

Var will be set to the position of the Field, Value or Sub-Value in which expression1 was found if indeed. If it was not found and expression6 was not specified then Var will be set to one position past the end of the searched dimension. If expression6 did specify the order of the elements then Var will be set to the position before which the element should be inserted to retain the specified order.

The statement must include one or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses. If expression1 is found in an element of the dynamic array, then it executes the statements defined by the THEN clause. If expression1 is not found in an element of the dynamic array, then it executes the statements defined by the ELSE clause.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When the LOCATE statement is used in International Mode, the statement will use the currently configured locale to determine the rules by which each string is considered less than or greater than the other will.

NOTES

See also: FIND, FINDSTR

EXAMPLE

Using LOCATE to sort an array.

   V.ARR = ''
   FOR V.I = 1 TO 1000
      V.ARR<V.I> = RND(1000)
   NEXT V.I
   V.SORTED = ''
    FOR V.I = 1 TO 1000
      V.IN = V.ARR<V.I>
      LOCATE V.IN IN V.SORTED<1> BY 'AN' SETTING V.INS.POSN ELSE NULL
      INS V.IN BEFORE V.SORTED<V.INS.POSN>
   NEXT V.I
   CRT MINIMUM(V.ARR), MAXIMUM(V.ARR)  ;* e.g. "0       998"
   CRT V.SORTED<1>, V.SORTED<1000>     ;* numbers should be the same as above

MATBUILD

This statement is used to create a dynamic array out of a dimensioned array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATBUILD variable FROM array{, expression1{, expression2}} { USING expression3}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable is the jBC variable into which the created dynamic array will be stored. Array is a previously dimensioned and assigned matrix from which the dynamic array will be created.

expression1 and expression2 should evaluate to numeric integers. expression1 specifies the array element from which the extraction starts; expression2 specifies the array element on which the extraction ends (inclusive).

By default, each array element is separated in the dynamic array by a field mark. By specifying expression3, the separator character can be changed. If expression3 evaluates to more than a single character, only the first character of the string is used.

NOTES

When specifying extraction starting and ending positions with multi-dimensional arrays, it is necessary to expand the matrix into its total number of variables for calculating the correct element number. See the information about dimensioned arrays earlier in this chapter for detailed instructions on calculating element numbers.

EXAMPLE

   DIM A(40)
   MAT A = 'VALUE '
   FOR V.I = 1 TO 40
       A(V.I) := V.I
   NEXT V.I
   MATBUILD Dynamic FROM A, 3, 7 USING ":"
   CRT Dynamic               ;* VALUE 3:VALUE 4:VALUE 5:VALUE 6:VALUE 7

Builds a 5 element string separated by ":" character. "MATBUILD Dynamic FROM A" builds a field mark separated dynamic array from every element contained in the matrix A.

MATCHES

MATCH or MATCHES clause applies pattern matching to an expression.

COMMAND SYNTAX

expression1 MATCHES expression2

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 may evaluate to any type. expression2 should evaluate to a valid pattern matching string as described below.

expression1 is then matched to the pattern supplied and a value of Boolean TRUE is returned if the pattern is matched. A value of Boolean FALSE is returned if the pattern is not matched.

expression2 can contain any number of patterns to match those separated by value marks. The value mark implies a logical OR of the specified patterns and the match will evaluate to Boolean TRUE if expression1 matches any of the specified patterns.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When using the MATCHES statement in International Mode, the statement will use the currently configured locale to determine the properties according to the Unicode Standard for each character in the expression. i.e., is the character alpha or numeric?

NOTES

The rule table shown below shows construction of pattern matching strings (n refers to any integer number).

Pattern | Explanation
nN | Matches a sequence of n digits
nA | Matches a sequence of n alpha characters
nC | Matches a sequence of n alpha characters
| or digits
nX | Matches a sequence of any characters
"string" | Matches the character sequence string exactly

Applies the pattern to all characters in expression1 and it must match all characters in the expression to evaluate as Boolean TRUE.

Specify the integer value 'n' as '0'. This will cause the pattern to match any number of characters of the specified type.

EXAMPLES

* T24 IDs matching
   transfer_id = 'FT130172HQJ4'
   CRT transfer_id MATCHES "'FT'5N5X"           ;*  1
   hist_id = 'FT130172HQJ4;1'
   CRT hist_id MATCHES "'FT'5N5X"               ;*  0
   CRT hist_id MATCHES "'FT'5N5X;1N"            ;*  1
* date
   start_date = '2011-10-25'
   CRT start_date MATCHES "4N'-'2N'-'2N"        ;*  1
* emulations compatibility
   cust_name = 'JOHN DORY'
   CRT cust_name MATCH "JOHN..."            ;*  1 under prime, 0 under jbase
   CRT cust_name MATCH "'JOHN'..."          ;*  1 under prime, 0 under jbase
   CRT cust_name MATCH "'JOHN'0X"           ;*  1 under both
   CRT cust_name MATCH "'John'..."          ;*  0 under both
* "C" - alphanumeric - isn't supported at all under prime
   CRT '2HQJ4' MATCHES "5C"                 ;* 1 under jbase emulation
* numbers
   CRT 9.99 MATCHES "0N'.'2N"               ;* 1
   CRT '.99' MATCHES "0N'.'2N"              ;* 1
* avoid messing up data with patterns (example for prime):
   cust_address = '3RD FLOOR, 17A ELM STREET'
   CRT cust_address MATCH "...17A..."   ;* 0 - 17A means 17 alpha characters
   CRT cust_address MATCH "...'17A'..." ;* 1 - here '17A' is a string to search

MATCHFIELD

This function is used to check a string against a match pattern.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATCHFIELD(string, pattern, field)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

field is an expression that evaluates to the portion of the match string to be returned.

If string matches pattern, the MATCHFIELD function returns the portion of string that matches the specified field in pattern. If string does not match pattern, or if string or pattern evaluates to the null value, the MATCHFIELD function returns an empty string. If field evaluates to the null value, the MATCHFIELD function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error.

pattern must contain specifiers to cover all characters contained in string. For example, the following statement returns an empty string because not all parts of string are specified in the pattern:

MATCHFIELD('XYZ123AB', '3X3N', 1)

To achieve a positive pattern match on the string above, use the following statement:

MATCHFIELD('XYZ123AB', '3X3N0X', 1)

This statement returns a value of "XYZ".

NOTES

See also: MATCHES operator for information about pattern matching.

EXAMPLES

    Q = MATCHFIELD('AA123BBB9', '2A0N3A0N', 3)
    PRINT 'Q=', Q                               ;*  Q=     BBB
    ADDR = '20 GREEN ST. NATICK, MA.,01234'
    ZIP = MATCHFIELD(ADDR, '0N0X5N', 3)
    PRINT 'ZIP=' , ZIP                          ;*  ZIP=   01234
    UNV = 'PART12345 BLUE AU'
    COL = MATCHFIELD(UNV, '10X4A3X', 2)
    PRINT 'COL= ', COL                          ;*  COL=   BLUE
    XYZ = MATCHFIELD('ABCDE1234', '2N3A4N', 1)
    PRINT 'XYZ= ', XYZ                          ;*  XYZ=
    ABC = MATCHFIELD('1234AB', '4N1A', 2)
    PRINT 'ABC= ', ABC                          ;*  ABC=

MATPARSE

MATPARSE statement is used to assign the elements of a matrix from the elements of a dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATPARSE array{, expression1{, expression2}} FROM variable1  \
        { USING expression3} SETTING variable2

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

array is a previously dimensioned matrix, which will be assigned from each element of the dynamic array. variable1 is the jBC variable from which the matrix array will be stored.

expression1 and expression2 should evaluate to numeric integers. expression1 specifies which element of the array the assignment will start with; expression2 specifies which element of the array the assignment will end with (inclusive).

By default, the dynamic array assumes the use of a field mark to separate each array element. By specifying expression3, the separator character can be changed. If expression3 evaluates to more than a single character, only the first character of the string is used.

As assignment will stop when the contents of the dynamic array have been exhausted, it can be useful to determine the number of matrix elements that were actually assigned to. If the SETTING clause is specified then variable2 will be set to the number of elements of the array that were assigned to.

NOTES

When specifying starting and ending positions with multi-dimensional arrays, it is necessary to expand the matrix into its total number of variables to calculate the correct element number.

See the information about dimensioned arrays earlier in this section for detailed instructions on calculating element numbers.

EXAMPLES

   DIM dim_array(100)
   dyn_array = ''   ;     delim_array = ''
   FOR i = 1 TO 100
      dyn_array<-1> = i
      delim_array := i*2 : '-'
   NEXT i
* Full copy
   MATPARSE dim_array FROM dyn_array
   CRT dim_array(1)                 ;* 1
   CRT dim_array(100)               ;* 100
* Using different array delimiter
   MAT dim_array = 'Default'
   MATPARSE dim_array FROM delim_array USING '-'
   CRT dim_array(1)                 ;* 2
   CRT dim_array(100)               ;* 200
* Partial copy
   MAT dim_array = 'Default'
   MATPARSE dim_array, 3, 7 FROM dyn_array
   CRT dim_array(1)                 ;* Default
   CRT dim_array(3)                 ;* 1
   CRT dim_array(5)                 ;* 3
   CRT dim_array(100)               ;* Default
* "Over-copy"
   FOR i = 101 TO 103               ;* add 3 elements to dynamic array
      dyn_array<-1> = i
   NEXT i
   MAT dim_array = 'Default'
   MATPARSE dim_array FROM dyn_array
   CRT dim_array(1)                 ;* 1
   CRT dim_array(100)               ;* 100
   the_extra = dim_array(0)           ;* all excess elements are here
   CHANGE @FM TO '>>>' IN the_extra
   CRT the_extra                        ;* 101>>>102>>>103
* 2-dimensioned array population: "left-to-right":
   DIM two_dim_array(100,2)
   MATPARSE two_dim_array FROM dyn_array
   CRT two_dim_array(1,1)                 ;* 1
   CRT two_dim_array(1,2)                 ;* 2
   CRT two_dim_array(2,1)                 ;* 3
   CRT two_dim_array(2,2)                 ;* 4
   CRT two_dim_array(50,2)                ;* 100
   CRT DQUOTE(two_dim_array(100,1))       ;* ""

MATREAD

The MATREAD statement allows a record stored in a jBASE file to be read and mapped directly into a dimensioned array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATREAD array FROM {variable1,} expression { SETTING setvar } \
        { ON ERROR statements } \
        { LOCKED statements} { THEN | ELSE statements}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

array should be a previously dimensioned array, which will be used to store the record to be read. If specified,

variable1 should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable1 is not specified then the default file is assumed. The expression should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

If no record is found and the record could be read from the file then it is mapped into the array and executes the THEN statements (if any). If the record cannot be read from the file then array is unchanged and executes the ELSE statements (if any).

If the record could not be read because another process already had a lock on the record then any one of the two actions is taken. If the LOCKED clause was specified in the statement then the statements dependent on it are executed. If no LOCKED clause was specified then the statement blocks (hangs) until the other process releases the lock. If a LOCKED clause is used and the read is successful, a lock will be set.

If the SETTING clause is specified, setvar will be set to the number of fields in the record on a successful read. If the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, it executes the statements following the ON ERROR clause for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

The record is mapped into the array using a predefined algorithm. The record is expected to consist of a number of field separated records, which are then assigned one at a time to each successive element of the matrix.

See the NOTES on matrix organization earlier in this section for details of multi dimensional arrays.

If there are more fields in the record than elements in the array, then the final element of the array will be assigned all remaining fields. If there were fewer fields in the record than elements in the array then the remaining array elements will be assigned a null value.

If multi-values are read into an array element they will then be referenced individually as:

  Array(n)<1,m>

not

  Array(n)<m>

EXAMPLES

MATREAD Xref FROM CFile, "XREF" ELSE MAT Xref = ''

MATREAD Ind FROM IFile, "INDEX" ELSE MAT Ind = 0

MATREAD record FROM filevar, id SETTING val ON ERROR
PRINT "Error number " :val: " occurred which prevented record from being read."
   STOP
END THEN
   PRINT 'Record read successfully'
END ELSE
   PRINT 'Record not on file'
END
PRINT "Number of attributes in record = " : val

MATREADU

MATREADU statement allows a record stored in a jBASE file to be read and mapped directly into a dimensioned array. The record will also be locked for update by the program.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATREADU array FROM {variable1,} expression { SETTING setvar } \
        { ON ERROR statements } \
        { LOCKED statements } { THEN | ELSE statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

array should be a previously dimensioned array, which will be used to store the record to be read. If specified, variable1 should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable1 is not specified then the default file is assumed. The expression should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

If found, the record could be read from the file then it is mapped into array and executes the THEN statements (if any). If the record cannot be read from the file for some reason then array is unchanged and executes the ELSE statements (if any).

If the record could not be read because another process already had a lock on the record then one of two actions is taken. If the LOCKED clause was specified in the statement then the statements dependent on it are executed. If no LOCKED clause was specified then the statement blocks (hangs) until the other process releases the lock.

If the SETTING clause is specified, setvar will be set to the number of fields in the record on a successful read. If the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

The record is mapped into the array using a predefined algorithm. The record is expected to consist of a number of Field separated records, which are then assigned one at a time to each successive element of the matrix. See the NOTES on matrix organization earlier in this section for details of the layout of multi dimensional arrays.

If there were more fields in the record than elements in the array, then the final element of the array will be assigned all remaining fields. If there were fewer fields in the record than elements in the array then remaining array elements will be assigned a null value.

If multi-values are read into an array element then they will be referenced individually as:

Array(n)<1,m>

not

Array(n)<m>

EXAMPLES

MATREADU Xref FROM CFile, "XREF" ELSE MAT Xref = ''
MATREADU Ind FROM IFile, "INDEX" LOCKED
   GOSUB InformUserLock ;* Say it is locked
END THEN
   GOSUB InformUserOk ;* Say we got it
END ELSE
   MAT Ind = 0 ;* It was not there
END

MATREADU record FROM filevar, id SETTING val ON ERROR
   PRINT "Error number " :val: " occurred which prevented record from being read"
   STOP
END LOCKED
   PRINT "Record is locked"
END THEN
   PRINT 'Record read successfully'
END ELSE
   PRINT 'Record not on file'
END
PRINT "Number of attributes in record = " : val

MATWRITE

The MATWRITE statement transfers the entire contents of a dimensioned array to a specified record on disc.

COMMAND SYNTAX

MATWRITE array TO | ON {variable,} expression { SETTING setvar }  \
       { ON ERROR statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

array should be a previously dimensioned and initialized array. If specified, variable should be a previously opened file variable (i.e. the subject of an OPEN statement). If variable is not specified the default file variable is used. expression should evaluate to the name of the record in the file.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the write succeeds, setvar will be set to the number of attributes read into the array.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the write fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

The compiler will check that the variable specified is a dimensioned array before its use in the statement.

EXAMPLES

DIM A(8)
MAT A = 99
....
MATWRITE A ON "NewArray" SETTING ErrorCode ON ERROR
   CRT "Error: " :ErrorCode: " Record could not be written."
END
...
MATWRITE A ON RecFile, "OldArray"

OBJEXCALLBACK

jBASE OBjEX provides the facility to call a subroutine from a front-end program written in a tool that supports OLE, such as Delphi or Visual Basic. The OBJEXCALLBACK statement allows communication between the subroutine and the calling OBjEX program.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OBJEXCALLBACK expression1, expression2 THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 and expression2 can contain any data. They are returned to the OBjEX program where they are defined as variants.

If the subroutine containing the OBJEXCALLBACK statement is not called from an OBjEX program (using the Call Method) then the ELSE clause will be taken.

NOTES

The OBJEXCALLBACK statement is designed to allow jBC subroutines to temporarily return to the calling environment to handle exception conditions or prompt for additional information. After servicing this event, the code should return control to the jBC program to ensure that the proper clean up operations are eventually made. The two parameters can be used to pass data between the jBC and OBjEX environments in both directions. They are defined as Variants in the OBjEX environment and as normal variables in the jBC environment.

See the OBjEX documentation for more information.

EXAMPLE

param1 = "SomeActionCode"
param2 = ProblemItem
OBJEXCALLBACK param1, param2 THEN
* this routine was called from ObjEX
END ELSE
* this routine was not called from ObjEX
END

OCONV

OCONV statement converts internal representations of data to their external form.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OCONV(expression1, expression2)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 may evaluate to any data type but must be relevant to the conversion code.

expression2 should evaluate to a conversion code from the list below. Alternatively, expression2 may evaluate to a user exit known to the jBC language or supplied by the user.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

Description of date, time, number and currency conversions when used in ICONV and International Mode

NOTES

OCONV will return the result of the conversion of expression1 by expression2. Shown below are valid conversion codes:

Conversion | Action
D{n{c}} | Converts an internal date to an external date format.
| The numeric argument n specifies the field width
| allowed for the year and can be 0 to 4 (default 4).
| The character 'c' causes the date to be return in the
| form ddcmmcyyyy. If it is not specified then the month
| name is returned in abbreviated form.
DI | Allows the conversion of an external date to the
| internal format even though an output conversion
| is expected.
DD | Returns the day in the current month.
DM | Returns the number of the month in the year.
DMA | Returns the name of the current month.
DJ | Returns the number of the day in the year (0-366).
DQ | Returns the quarter of the year as a number 1 to 4.
DW | Returns the day of the week as a number 1 to 7
| (Monday is 1).
DWA | Returns the name of the day of the week.
DY{n} | Returns the year in a field of n characters.
F | Given a prospective filename for a command such as
| CREATE-FILE this conversion will return a filename
| that is acceptable to the version of UNIX TAFC is
| running on.
MCA | Removes all but alphabetic characters from the input
| string.
MC/A | Removes all but the NON-alphabetic characters in the
| input string.
MCN | Removes all but numeric characters in the input string.
MC/N | Removes all but NON numeric characters in the input
| string.
MCB | Returns just the alphabetic and numeric characters from
| the input string.
MC/B | Removes the alphabetic and numeric characters from
| their input string.
MCC;s1;s2 | Replaces all occurrences of string s1 with string s2.
MCL | Converts all upper case characters in the string to
| lower case characters.
MCU | Converts all lower case characters in the string to
| upper case characters.
MCT | Capitalizes each word in the input string; e.g. JIM
| converts to Jim.
MCP{c} | Converts all non-printable characters to a period
| character "." in the input string. When supplied use
| the character
| "c" in place of the period.
MCPN{n} | In the same manner as the MCP conversion, it replaces
| all non-printable characters. The ASCII hexadecimal
| value
| follows the replacing character.
MCNP{n} | Performs the opposite conversion to MCPN. The ASCII
| hexadecimal value following the tilde character
| converts to its
| original binary character value.
MCDX | Converts the decimal value in the input string to its
| hexadecimal equivalent.
MCXD | Converts the hexadecimal value in the input string to
| its decimal equivalent.
Gncx | Extracts x groups separated by character c skipping n
| groups, from the input string.
MT{HS} | Performs time conversions.
MD | Converts the supplied integer value to a decimal value.
MP | Converts a packed decimal number to an integer value.
MX | Converts ASCII input to hexadecimal characters.
T | Performs file translations given a cross-reference
| table in a record in a file.

EXAMPLES

Date and time:

   CRT OCONV(1, 'D')         ;* 01 JAN 1968
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'D' )    ;* here and below output for 30 MAY 2013
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'D2' )   ;* 30 MAY 13
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'D4/' )  ;* 05/30/2013
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DY' )   ;* 2013
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DY2' )  ;* 13
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DQ' )   ;* 2 (quarter)
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DM' )   ;* 5 (month number)
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DMA' )  ;* MAY
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DD' )   ;* 30
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DJ' )   ;* 150 (number of a day in the year)
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DW' )   ;* 4 (day number in a week, starting from Monday)
   CRT OCONV( DATE(), 'DWA' )  ;* THURSDAY
   CRT OCONV( TIME(), 'MT' )   ;* 20:04
   CRT OCONV( TIME(), 'MTS' )  ;* 20:04:08
   CRT OCONV(1, 'MTS')       ;* 00:00:01
* difference of 2 dates (in days)
   CRT ICONV('20121231', 'D') - ICONV('20111231', 'D')   ;* 366
* Check if a year is a leap one
   CRT OCONV( ICONV('20131231', 'D4'), 'DJ' )    ;*  365
   CRT OCONV( ICONV('20161231', 'D4'), 'DJ' )    ;*  366

Strings:

* split a string
   the_string = 'LONG STRING TO BE SPLIT'
   the_split = FMT(the_string, '10L')
   CRT OCONV(the_split, 'MCP')         ;* LONG STRIN.G TO BE SP.LIT
* hexadecimal output
   CRT OCONV(the_split, 'MX')
* Output:
* 4C4F4E4720535452494EFB4720544F204245205350FB4C495420202020202020
*
* Remove non-alphabetic symbols:
   CRT OCONV(the_split, 'MCA')     ;* LONGSTRINGTOBESPLIT
* Remove all alphabetic symbols:
   CRT OCONV( OCONV(the_split, 'MC/A'), 'MX' )  ;* 20FB202020FB20202020202020
* Note FB symbols in the output above.. see what's that
   CRT OCONV('FB', 'MCXD')    ;* 251 a.k.a. @TM
   CHANGE @TM TO '->' IN the_split ; CRT the_split ;* LONG STRIN->G TO BE SP->LIT
* Remove non-numeric symbols:
   CRT OCONV('another 1 bites the dust', 'MCN')    ;* 1
* Remove all numeric symbols:
   CRT OCONV('another 1 bites the dust', 'MC/N')   ;* another  bites the dust
* formatting
   CRT SQUOTE( FMT(the_string, '30L') )    ;* 'LONG STRING TO BE SPLIT       '
   CRT SQUOTE( FMT(the_string, '30R') )    ;* '       LONG STRING TO BE SPLIT'
* replace some data
   CRT OCONV(the_string, 'MCC;STRING;DATA')  ;* LONG DATA TO BE SPLIT
* change case
   CRT OCONV(the_string, 'MCL')  ;* long string to be split
   CRT OCONV('do it', 'MCU')     ;* DO IT
   CRT OCONV(the_string, 'MCT')  ;* Long String To Be Split
* extract delimited fields: skip 1 space-delimited word, take 3 from that point
   CRT OCONV(the_string, 'G1 3')  ;* STRING TO BE

Numbers:

* amounts
   amount_fcy = 1234
   CRT FMT(amount_fcy, 'R%7')   ;*       0001234
   amount_fcy += 0.56
   CRT FMT(amount_fcy, 'R2*19')              ;*  ************1234.56
   CRT SQUOTE( FMT(amount_fcy, 'L2,#19') )     ;*  '1,234.56           '
   CRT FMT(-amount_fcy, 'R2,C&*$#15')        ;*           $1,234.56CR
   CRT FMT(amount_fcy,'L0')                  ;* 1235
* phone numbers
   CRT FMT(1234567890, 'R((###) ###-###)')       ;* (234) 567-890
   CRT FMT(74952223355, 'R(+# (#3) #3-#2-#2)')   ;* +7 (495) 222-33-55
* FMT() and OCONV() are often interchangeable;
* though it's not the case for next 2 lines...
   CRT DQUOTE( FMT(123456.78, 'R2,$#15') )           ;*  "    $123,456.78"
   CRT DQUOTE( OCONV(123456.78, 'R2,$#15') )         ;*  Error in Range Test

User exits:

   CRT OCONV("", "U50BB")        ;* port number and user name
   HUSH ON
   EXECUTE 'SELECT .'
   HUSH OFF
   CRT OCONV("", "U30E0")        ;* number of items in active SELECT list
* sleep
   start_time = TIME()  ;  dummy = OCONV(3, "U307A")
   CRT TIME() - start_time        ;* 3
* reverse a string
   CRT OCONV('desrever saw gnirtS', "U51AA")
* remove duplicate consecutive characters
   CRT OCONV('hhahhahh', "U31AC")        ;* haha

See also: FMT function.

OCONVS

OCONVS function converts the elements of dynamic.array to a specified format for external output.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OCONVS(dynamic.array, conversion)

Converts the elements to the external output format specified by conversion and returns it in a dynamic array.

conversion must evaluate to one or more conversion codes separated by value marks (ASCII 253).

If multiple codes are used, they are applied from left to right as follows: the left-most conversion code is applied to the element, the next conversion code to the right is then applied to the result of the first conversion, and so on.

If dynamic.array evaluates to null, it returns null. If any element of dynamic.array is null, it returns null for that element. If conversion evaluates to null, the OCONVS function fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

The STATUS function reflects the result of the conversion:

Code | Status
0 | The conversion is successful.
1 | Passes an invalid element to the OCONVS function; the
| original element
| is returned. If the invalid element is null, it returns
| null for that element.
| unless dynamic.array is null, in which case it returns
| null.
2 | The conversion code is invalid.

NOTES

For information about converting elements in a dynamic array to an internal format, see also: ICONVS function.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

Description of date, time, number and currency conversions when used in ICONV and International Mode.

ONGOTO

The ON...GOSUB and ON...GOTO statements are used to transfer program execution to a label based upon a calculation.

COMMAND SYNTAX

ON expression GOTO label{, label...}

ON expression GOSUB label{, label...}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression should evaluate to an integer numeric value. Labels should be defined somewhere in the current source file.

ON GOTO will transfer execution to the labeled source code line in the program.

ON GOSUB will transfer execution to the labeled subroutine within the source code.

NOTES

Use the value of expression as an index to the list of labels supplied. If the expression evaluates to 1 then the first label will jump to 2 then the second label will be used and so on.

If the program was compiled when the emulation included the setting generic_pick = true, then no validations are performed on the index to see if it is valid. Therefore, if the index is out of range this instruction will take no action and report no error.

If the program was compiled for other emulations then the index will be range checked. If found that the index is less than 1, it is assumed to be 1 and a warning message is issued. If the index is found to be too big, then the last label in the list will be used to transfer execution and a warning message will be issued.

EXAMPLE

   cntrl_var = 1
*
   ON cntrl_var GOSUB BIGGER
   ON cntrl_var GOSUB EXCEPT, SMALLER
   ON cntrl_var GOSUB SMALLER
*
   STOP
*
BIGGER:
   cntrl_var ++
   CRT cntrl_var
   RETURN
*
SMALLER:
   cntrl_var --
   CRT cntrl_var
   RETURN
*
EXCEPT:
   CRT 'Error occured'
   RETURN
*
END

Output of this program:

    2
    1
    0

OPEN

OPEN statement is used to open a file or device to a descriptor variable within jBC.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OPEN {expression1,}expression2 TO {variable} { SETTING setvar } \
     THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The combination of expression1 and expression2 should evaluate to a valid file name of a file type that already installed on the jBASE system. If the file has a dictionary section to be opened by the statement then specify by the literal string "DICT" being specified in expression1. If specified, the variable will be used to hold the descriptor for the file. It should then be to access the file using READ and WRITE. If no file descriptor variable is supplied, then the file will be opened to the default file descriptor.

Specific data sections of a multi level file may be specified by separating the section name from the file name by a "," char in expression2.

If the OPEN statement fails, it will execute any statements associated with an ELSE clause. If the OPEN is successful, it will execute any statements associated with a THEN clause. Note that the syntax requires either one or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses.

If specifying the SETTING clause and the open fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

The OPEN statement uses the environment variable JEDIFILEPATH to search for the named file. If there is no defined named file, it will search the current working directory followed by the home directory of the current process. The file that is the subject of the OPEN statement can be of any type known to the jBASE system. Its type will be determined and correctly opened transparently to the application, which need not be aware of the file type.

A jBC program can open an unlimited amount of files (up the limit set by OS settings).

EXAMPLE

   EXECUTE 'DELETE-FILE DATA F.TEMP'
   EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP'
   V.REC.INIT = 'LINE 1' :@FM: 'LINE 2' :@FM: 'LINE 3'
   WRITE V.REC.INIT TO F.TEMP, 'REC1'
   CLOSE F.TEMP

EXAMPLE 2

Get list of current processes and output port number and PID for each:

   OPEN SYSTEM(1027) TO PROC ELSE STOP 201, "PROC"
   SELECT PROC TO SEL
   LOOP
   WHILE READNEXT key FROM SEL DO
      READ PROCESSRECORD FROM PROC, key ELSE CRT "Read Error"  ;  STOP
      V.PORTNO = PROCESSRECORD<1>
      V.PID = PROCESSRECORD<4>
      PRINT FMT(V.PORTNO, '2R') : '|' : FMT(V.PID, '8R')
   REPEAT

OPENDEV

OPENDEV statement is used to open a device (or file) for sequential writing and/or reading.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OPENDEV Device TO FileVar { LOCKED statements } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Device specifies the target device or file.

FileVar contains the file descriptor of the file when the open was successful.

Statements are conditional jBC statements.

NOTES

If the device does not exist or cannot be opened it executes the ELSE clause. Once open it takes a lock on the device. If the lock cannot be taken then the LOCKED clause is executed if it exists otherwise the ELSE clause is executed. The specified device can be a regular file, pipe or special device file. Regular file types only take locks. Once open the file pointer is set to the first line of sequential data.

EXAMPLE

OPENDEV "\\.\TAPE0" TO tape.drive ELSE STOP

Opens the Windows default tape drive and prepares it for sequential processing.

For more information on sequential processing, see READSEQ, WRITESEQ the sequential processing example.

OPENINDEX

OPENINDEX statement is used to open a particular index definition for a particular file. This index file variable can later be used with the SELECT statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OPENINDEX filename,indexname TO indexvar { SETTING setvar } THEN  \
  | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

filename should correspond to a valid file which has at least one index.

indexname should correspond to an index created for the filename.

indexvar is the variable that holds the descriptor for the index.

If the OPEN statement fails then it will execute any statements associated with an ELSE clause. If the OPEN is successful then it will execute any statements associated with a THEN clause. Note that the syntax requires either one or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the OPEN fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

EXAMPLES

OPENINDEX "CUSTOMER","IXLASTNAME" TO custlastname.ix SETTING errval ELSE
  CRT "OPENINDEX failed for file CUSTOMER, index IXLASTNAME"
  ABORT
END

OPENPATH

OPENPATH statement is used to open a file (given an absolute or relative path) to a descriptor variable within jBC. See also: OPEN statement.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OPENPATH expression1 TO {variable} { SETTING setvar } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression1 should be an absolute or relative path to the file including the name of the file to be opened. If specified, variable will be used to hold the descriptor for the file. It should then be to access the file using READ and WRITE. If no file descriptor variable is supplied, then the file will be opened to the default file descriptor.

If the OPENPATH statement fails it will execute any statements associated with an ELSE clause. If successful, the OPENPATH will execute any statements associated with a THEN clause. Note that the syntax requires either one or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the open fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

The path specified may be either a relative or an absolute path and must include the name of the jBASE file being opened.

The file that is the subject of the OPENPATH statement can be of any type known to the jBASE system. Its type will be determined and correctly opened transparently to the application, which need not be aware of the file type.

A jBC program can open an unlimited amount of files.

EXAMPLES

OPENPATH "C:\Home\CUSTOMERS" TO F.Customers ELSE
   ABORT 201, "CUSTOMERS"
END

Opens the file CUSTOMERS (located in C:) to its own file descriptor F.Customers

OPEN "F:\Users\data\CUSTOMERS" ELSE ABORT 201, "CUSTOMERS"

Opens the CUSTOMERS file (located in F:) to the default file variable.

OPENSEQ

OPENSEQ is used to open a file for sequential writing and/or reading.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OPENSEQ Path{,File} {READONLY} TO FileVar { LOCKED statements }  \
        THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Path specifies the relative or absolute path of the target directory or file.

File specifies additional path information of the target file.

FileVar contains the file descriptor of the file when the open was successful.

Statements are conditional jBC statements.

NOTES

If the file does not exist or cannot be opened it then executes the ELSE clause. However, if JBASICEMULATE is set for Sequoia (use value "seq") emulation then OPENSEQ will create the file if it does not exist. This behavior can also be achieved by specifying "openseq_creates = true" in Config_EMULATE for the emulation being used. Once open a lock is taken on the file. If the lock cannot be taken then the LOCKED clause is executed if it exists otherwise the ELSE clause is executed. If specified the READONLY process takes a read lock on the file, otherwise it takes a write lock. The specified file can be a regular, pipe or special device file. Locks are only taken on regular file types. Once open the file pointer is set to the first line of sequential data.

EXAMPLE 1

Create a flat file and write to it. If file already exists - append data to it:

   V.DIR.OUT = '.'
   V.FILE.OUT = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ V.DIR.OUT, V.FILE.OUT TO F.FILE.OUT THEN
      SEEK F.FILE.OUT, 0, 2 ELSE  ;* go to the end
         CRT 'Seek error'
         STOP
      END
      WRITESEQ 'One more line' TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
         CRT 'Write error'
         STOP
      END
   END ELSE
      WRITESEQ 'Line 1' TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
         CRT 'Write error'
         STOP
      END
   END

EXAMPLE 2

Run the previous example several times, then - this one (flat file will be read and proceeded line-by-line):

   V.DIR.IN = '.'
   V.FILE.IN = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ V.DIR.IN, V.FILE.IN TO F.FILE.IN ELSE
      CRT 'Failed to open', V.FILE.IN
      STOP
   END
   V.LINE.NO = 0
   LOOP
      READSEQ V.LINE FROM F.FILE.IN ELSE BREAK
      V.LINE.NO ++
      CRT '[' : V.LINE.NO : ']' : V.LINE
   REPEAT

Output will look like:

    [1]Line 1
    [2]One more line
    [3]One more line
    ...

OSBREAD

OSBREAD command reads data from a file starting at a specified byte location for a certain length of bytes, and assigns the data to a variable.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OSBREAD var FROM file.var [ AT byte.expr ] LENGTH length.expr  \
        [ ON ERROR statements ]

OSBREAD performs an operating system block read on a UNIX or Windows file.

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

var specifies a variable to which the data read is assigned.

FROM file.var specifies a file from which the data is read.

AT byte.expr specifies a location inside the file from where the data reading operation is to start. If byte.expr is 0, the read begins at the beginning of the file.

LENGTH length.expr specifies length of data to be read from the file, starting at byte.expr. length.expr cannot be longer than the maximum string length determined by your system configuration.

ON ERROR statements are statements executed if a fatal error occurs (if the file is not open, or if the file is a read-only file). If you do not specify the ON ERROR clause, the program will terminate under such fatal error conditions.

STATUS Function Return Values After you execute OSBREAD, the STATUS function returns either 0 or a failure code.

NOTE

Before you use OSBREAD, you must open the file by using the OSOPEN or OPENSEQ command.

jBASE uses the ASCII 0 character [CHAR (0)] as a string-end delimiter. Therefore, ASCII 0 cannot be used in any string variable within jBASE. OSBREAD converts CHAR(0) to CHAR(128) when reading a block of data.

EXAMPLE

In the following example, the program test.b reads itself and outputs its contents to the screen:

   OSOPEN 'test.b' TO MYFILE ELSE STOP
   OSBREAD Data FROM MYFILE AT 0 LENGTH 10000
   CRT Data

OSBWRITE

OSBWRITE command writes an expression to a sequential file starting at a specified byte location.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OSBWRITE expr { ON | TO } file.var [ AT byte.expr ] [ NODELAY ]  \
         [ ON ERROR statements ]

OSBWRITE immediately writes a file segment out to the UNIX, Windows NT, or Windows 2000 file. There is no necessity to specify a length expression because the number of bytes in expr is already written to the file.

OSBWRITE converts CHAR (128) back to CHAR(0) when writing a block of characters.

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expr specifies the expression to be written in the file.

ON | TO file.var specifies the file on which the expression is to be written.

AT byte.expr specifies the byte number from where the expression is to be written. For example, if byte.expr is 0, then the expression is written in the beginning of the file.

NODELAY forces an immediate write.

ON ERROR statements are the statements executed if the OSBWRITE statement fails with fatal error, I/O error, or jBASE cannot find the file. If you do not specify the ON ERROR clause and a fatal error occurs, the program will terminate.

STATUS Function Return Values

After you execute OSBWRITE, the STATUS function returns either 0 or a failure code.

Code | Description
0 | The write was successful.
1 | The write failed.

NOTES

Before you use OSBWRITE, you must open the file by using the OSOPEN or OPENSEQ command.

jBASE uses the ASCII 0 character [CHAR (0)] as a string-end delimiter. Therefore, ASCII 0 cannot be used in any string variable within jBASE. If jBASE reads a string that contains CHAR(0) characters by using OSBREAD, those characters are converted to CHAR(128).

EXAMPLE

In the following example, the program statement writes the data in MYPIPE to the opened file starting from the beginning of the file:

OSBWRITE Data ON MYPIPE AT 0

OSOPEN

OSOPEN command opens a sequential file that does not use CHAR (10) as the line delimiter.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OSOPEN filename TO file.var [ ON ERROR statements ] { THEN | ELSE } statements

Read/write access mode is the default. Override this access mode by using READONLY and WRITEONLY.

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

filename specifies the file to be opened. Filename must include the entire path name unless the file resides in the current directory.

TO file.var specifies a variable to contain a pointer to the file.

ON ERROR statements are statements executed when the OSOPEN statement fails with fatal error, I/O error, or JBASE cannot find the file. If you do not specify the ON ERROR clause and a fatal error occurs, the program will enter the debugger.

THEN statements executes if the read is successful.

ELSE statements executes if the read is not successful or the record (or ID) does not exist.

NOTES

After opening a sequential file with OSOPEN, use OSBREAD to read a block of data from the file, or OSBWRITE to write a block of data to the file. You also can use READSEQ to read a record from the file, or WRITESEQ or WRITESEQF to write a record to the file, if the file is not a named pipe. (READSEQ, WRITESEQ, WRITESEQF are line-oriented commands that use CHAR (10) as the line delimiter.)

EXAMPLE

In the following example, the program statement opens the file 'MYSLIPPERS' as SLIPPERS.

OSOPEN 'MYSLIPPERS' TO SLIPPERS ELSE STOP

OSREAD

OSREAD reads an OS file.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OSREAD Variable FROM expression { ON ERROR Statements }  \
      { THEN | ELSE } Statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Variable specifies the variable which is to be assigned to the read data.

Expression specifies the full file path. If the file resides in the JEDIFILEPATH then just the file name is required.

ON ERROR Statements are conditional jBC statements to be executed when the OSREAD statement fails with fatal error (because the file is not open), I/O error, or jBASE cannot find the file. If you do not specify the ON ERROR clause and a fatal error occurs, the program will terminate.

THEN | ELSE: If the OSREAD statement fails, it will execute any statements associated with an ELSE clause. If the OSREAD is successful, it will execute any statements associated with a THEN clause. Note that the syntax requires either one or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses.

WARNING

Do not use OSREAD on large files. The jBC OSREAD command reads an entire sequential file and assigns the contents of the file to a variable. If the file is too large for the program memory, the program aborts and generates a runtime error message. On large files, use OSBREAD or READSEQ. jBASE uses the ASCII 0 character (CHAR (0)) as a string-end delimiter. ASCII 0 is not useable within string variable in jBC. This command converts CHAR(0) to CHAR(128) when reading a block of data.

NOTE

OSREAD doesn't include the LF character after the last line in the file to the resulting variable:

EXAMPLE

   V.DIR.OUT = '.'  ;   V.FILE.OUT = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ V.DIR.OUT, V.FILE.OUT TO F.FILE.OUT THEN
      WEOFSEQ F.FILE.OUT
   END ELSE
      CREATE F.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'File create error'  ;  STOP
   END
   V.BUFFER = STR('.', 999)
   LOOP
      WRITESEQ V.BUFFER TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'Write error'  ;  STOP
      V.FILE.SIZE = DIR(V.FILE.OUT)<1>
      CRT V.FILE.SIZE
   UNTIL V.FILE.SIZE GE 10000
   REPEAT
   CLOSESEQ F.FILE.OUT
   OSREAD V.ALL FROM V.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'Read error'  ;  STOP
   CRT LEN(V.ALL)
   CRT DQUOTE( RIGHT(V.ALL, 20) )

Output:

    1000
    2000
    3000
    4000
    5000
    6000
    7000
    8000
    9000
    10000
    9999
    "...................."

OSWRITE

The OSWRITE command writes the contents of an expression to a sequential file.

COMMAND SYNTAX

OSWRITE expr { ON | TO } filename [ ON ERROR statements ]

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expr specifies the expression to be written into a file.

ON | TO filename specifies the name of a sequential file to which the expression is to be written.

ON ERROR statements are statements to be executed when the OSWRITE statement fails with fatal error (because the file is not open), I/O error, or jBASE cannot find the file. If you do not specify the ON ERROR clause and if a fatal error occurs, the program will enter the debugger.

NOTE

JBASE uses the ASCII 0 character [CHAR(0)] as a string-end delimiter. For this reason, you cannot use ASCII 0 in any string variable in jBASE. If jBASE reads a string with a CHAR(0) character, and then the character is converted to CHAR(128), OSWRITE converts CHAR(128) to CHAR(0) when writing a block of characters.

EXAMPLE

In the following example, the program segment writes the contents of FOOTWEAR variable to the file called "PINK" in the directory '/usr/local/myslippers'.

OSWRITE FOOTWEAR ON "/usr/local/myslippers/PINK"

PRINTERR

PRINTERR statement is used to print standard jBASE error messages.

COMMAND SYNTAX

PRINTERR expression

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Field 1 of the expression should evaluate to the numeric or string name of a valid error message in the jBASE error message file. If the error message requires parameters then these can be passed to the message as subsequent fields of the expression.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When the PRINTERR statement is used in International Mode, the error message file to be used, i.e. the default "jBASICmessages" or other as configured via the error message environment variable, will be suffixed with the current locale. For example, if the currently configured locale is "fr_FR" then the statement will attempt to find the specified error message record id in the "jBASICmessages_fr_FR" error message file. If the file cannot be found then the country code will be discarded and just the language code used. i.e. the file "jBASICmessages_fr" will be used. If this file is also not found then the error message file "jBASICmessages" will be used.

NOTES

The PRINTERR statement is most useful for user-defined messages that have been added to the standard set.

You should be very careful when typing this statement it is very similar to the PRINTER statement. Although this is not ideal, the PRINTERR statement must be supported for compatibility with older systems.

EXAMPLE

   PRINTERR 201 : CHAR(254) : "CUSTOMERS"

Output:

     ∗∗ Error [ 201 ] ∗∗
    Unable to open file CUSTOMERS

READBLK

READBLK statement is used to read a block of data of a specified length from a file opened for sequential processing and assign it to a variable.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READBLK variable FROM file.variable, blocksize { THEN statements \
        [ ELSE statements ] | ELSE statements }

The READBLK statement reads a block of data beginning at the current position in the file and continuing for blocksize bytes and assigns it to variable. The current position is reset to just beyond the last readable byte.

file.variable specifies a file previously opened for sequential processing.

If the data can be read from the file, the THEN statements are executed; any ELSE statements are ignored. If the file is not readable or if the end of file is encountered, the ELSE statements are executed and the THEN statements are ignored. If the ELSE statements are executed, variable is set to an empty string. If either file.variable or blocksize evaluates to null, the READBLK statement fails and the program enters the debugger.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When using the READBLK statement in International Mode, care must be taken to ensure that the input variable is handled properly subsequent to the READBLK statement. The READBLK statement requires that a "bytecount" be specified, however when manipulating variables in International Mode character length rather than byte lengths are usually used and hence possible confusion or program malfunction can occur.

If requiring character data convert the input variable from 'binary/latin1' to UTF-8 byte sequence via the UTF8 function.

It is recommended that the READBLK/WRITEBLK statements not be used when executing in International Mode. Similar functionality can be obtained via the READSEQ/WRITESEQ statement, which can be used to read/writecharacters a line at a time from a file.

NOTE

A new line in UNIX files is one byte long, whereas in Windows NT it is two bytes long. This means that for a file with newlines, the same READBLK statement may return a different set of data depending on the operating system the file is stored under.

The difference between the READSEQ statement and the READBLK statement is that the READBLK statement reads a block of data of a specified length, whereas the READSEQ statement reads a single line of data.

EXAMPLE

   IF NOT( GETENV('TAFC_HOME', V.HOME) ) THEN
      CRT 'TAFC_HOME not defined'
      STOP
   END
   V.FILE.IN = 'RELEASE'
   V.FILE.INFO = DIR(V.HOME : '/' : V.FILE.IN)
   V.SIZE = V.FILE.INFO<1>
   OPENSEQ V.HOME, V.FILE.IN TO F.FILE.IN ELSE
      CRT 'Failed to open', V.FILE.IN
      STOP
   END
   V.BLK.SIZE = MINIMUM(V.SIZE :@FM: 512)
   READBLK V.TEXT FROM F.FILE.IN, V.BLK.SIZE ELSE
      CRT 'Failed to read', V.FILE.IN
      STOP
   END
   CRT V.TEXT[1, INDEX(V.TEXT, CHAR(10), 1)]   ;* 1st line, e.g.:
                                               ;* jBase Release : R11.0.0.0

READL

READL statement allows a process to read a record from a previously opened file into a variable and takes a read-only shared lock on the record. It respects all records locked with the READU statement but allows other processes using READL to share the same lock.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READL variable1 FROM {variable2,} expression { SETTING setvar }  \
      { ON ERROR statements } \
      { LOCKED statements } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier into which the record will be read.

variable2, if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement if variable2 is not specified then the default file is assumed.

The expression should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

READL takes a read-only shared record lock whereas READU takes an exclusive lock. This means that any record, which is read using READL, can also be read by another process using a READL. In other words, the lock on the record is 'shared' in that no READU lock against the same record can be taken.

Similarly, if READU takes a lock then READL will respect that lock. By comparison, READU takes an exclusive lock in that the one process retains control over the record.

The usage of READU is already well documented and understood. The usage of READL allows for an application to present a record to one or more users such that its integrity is ensured, i.e. the user(s) viewing the record can be assured that wysiwyg and that no updates to that record have been made whilst viewing the record.

While it is permissible to WRITE a record that has a READL lock, the intent of READL is to permit a 'read-only' shared lock and the act of WRITEing this record would not be considered good programming practice.

READ takes no lock at all and does not respect any lock taken with READU or READL. In other words, a READ can be performed at any time and on any record regardless of any existing locks.

Due to limitations on Windows platforms, the READL statement behaves the same as the READU statement, in other words they both take exclusive locks.

If the record could not be read because another process already had a READU lock on the record then one of two actions is taken. If the LOCKED clause was specified in the statement then the statements dependent on it are executed.

If no LOCKED clause was specified then the statement blocks (hangs) until the other process releases the lock. The SYSTEM (43) function can be used to determine which port has the lock.

If the statement fails to read the record then any statements associated with the ELSE clause will be executed. If the statement successfully reads the record then the statements associated with any THEN clause are executed.

Either or both of THEN and ELSE clauses must be specified with the statement.

The lock taken by the READL statement will be released by any of the following events however, be aware that the record will not be fully released until all shared locks have been released:

The same program with WRITE, WRITEV or MATWRITE statements writes to the record.

The same program with the DELETE statement deletes the record.

The record lock is released explicitly using the RELEASE statement.

The program stops normally or abnormally.

When a file is OPENed to a local file variable in a subroutine then the file is closed when the subroutine RETURNS so all locks taken on that file are released, including locks taken in a calling program. Files that are opened to COMMON variables are not closed so the locks remain intact.

EXAMPLE

   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO f_temp ELSE
      EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
      OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO f_temp ELSE
         CRT 'OPEN FAILED'
         STOP
      END
   END
   rec_id = 'REC1'
   READL record FROM f_temp, rec_id LOCKED
      CRT 'Lock failure'
      STOP
   END ELSE NULL
   CRT RECORDLOCKED(f_temp, rec_id)  ;* 2 under Windows, 1 under Unix

See also: WRITE, WRITEU, MATWRITE, MATWRITEU, RELEASE, and DELETE

READNEXT

READNEXT retrieves the next element in a list variable.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READNEXT variable1, variable2 { FROM variable3 } { SETTING setvar }  \
         { THEN | ELSE statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the variable into which the next element of the list will be read.

variable2 is used when the list has been retrieved externally from a SSELECT or similar TAFC command that has used an exploding sort directive. When specified, this variable will be set to the multi-value reference of the current element. For example, if the SSELECT used a BY-EXP directive on field 3 of the records in a file, the list will contain each record key in the file as many times as there are multi-values in the field. Each READNEXT instance will set variable2 to the multi-value in field 3 to which the element refers. This allows the multi-values in field 3 to be retrieved in sorted order.

If variable3 is specified with the FROM clause, the READNEXT operates on the list contained in variable3. If variable3 is not specified, the default select list variable will be assumed.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the read (to build the next portion of the list) fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

READNEXT can be used as an expression returning a Boolean TRUE or FALSE value. If an element is successfully read from the list, TRUE is returned. If the list was empty, FALSE is returned.

See also: SELECT, extensions for secondary indexes.

EXAMPLE

   EXECUTE 'DELETE-FILE DATA F.TEMP'
   EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP'
   V.REC.INIT = 'LINE 1' :@FM: 'LINE 2' :@FM: 'LINE 3'
   WRITE V.REC.INIT TO F.TEMP, 'REC1'
   WRITE V.REC.INIT TO F.TEMP, 'REC2'
   WRITE V.REC.INIT TO F.TEMP, 'REC3'
   CLOSE F.TEMP
   V.SEL = 'SSELECT F.TEMP TO 9'
   EXECUTE V.SEL
   READNEXT V.ID FROM 9 ELSE CRT 'READNEXT 1 FAILED'
   CRT 'NEXT:' : V.ID                                   ;* NEXT:REC1
   READNEXT V.ID FROM 9 ELSE CRT 'READNEXT 2 FAILED'
   CRT 'NEXT:' : V.ID                                   ;* NEXT:REC2

READT

READT statement is used to read a range of tape devices 0-9.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READT variable { FROM expression } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable is the variable that will receive any data read from the tape device.

expression should evaluate to an integer value in the range 0-9 and specifies from which tape channel to read data. If the FROM clause is not specified the READT will assume channel 0.

If the READT fails then the statements associated with any ELSE clause will be executed. SYSTEM (0) will return the reason for the failure as follows:

Code | Description
1 | There is no media attached to the channel.
2 | An end of file mark was found.

NOTES

A "tape" does not only refer to magnetic tape devices, but also any device that has been described to TAFC. Writing device descriptors for jBASE is beyond the scope of this manual.

If no tape device has been assigned to the specified channel the TAFC debugger is entered with an appropriate message.

Each instance of the READT statement will read the next record available on the device. The record size is not limited to a single tape block and the entire record will be returned whatever block size has been allocated by the T-ATT command.

EXAMPLE

LOOP
      READT TapeRec FROM 5 ELSE
          Reason = SYSTEM(0)
          IF Reason = 2 THEN BREAK ;* done
          CRT "ERROR"  ;  STOP
      END
REPEAT

READU

READU statement allows a program to read a record from previously opened file into variable. It respects record locking and locks the specified record for update.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READU variable1 FROM {variable2,} expression { SETTING setvar }  \
      { WAIT timeout } { ON ERROR statements } { LOCKED statements }  \
      THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier into which the record will be read.

variable2 if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified then the default file is assumed.

The expression should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If WAIT clause is specified and the record stated in Variable1 is already locked, READU waits 'timeout' milliseconds before executing LOCKED statement. If LOCKED clause is not specified WAIT clause does not effect to the READU behaviour. Without LOCKED clause READU is blocked until the lock is released regardless to the WAIT clause parameter.

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

If the record could not be read because another process already had a lock on the record then one of two actions is taken. If the LOCKED clause was specified in the statement then the statements dependent on it are executed. If no LOCKED clause was specified then the statement blocks (hangs) until the other process releases the lock. Use the SYSTEM (43) function to determine which port has the lock.

If the statement fails to read the record then any statements associated with the ELSE clause will be executed. If the statement successfully reads the record then the statements associated with any THEN clause are executed. Either or both of THEN and ELSE clauses must be specified with the statement.

The lock taken by the READU statement will be released by any of the following events:

The same program with WRITE, WRITEV or MATWRITE statements writes to the record.

The same program with the DELETE statement deletes the record.

The record lock is released explicitly using the RELEASE statement.

The program stops normally or abnormally.

When a file is OPENed to a local file variable in a subroutine then the file is closed when the subroutine RETURNS so all locks taken on that file are released, including locks taken in a calling program. Files that are opened to COMMON variables are not closed so the locks remain intact.

See also: WRITE, WRITEU, MATWRITE, MATWRITEU, RELEASE, and DELETE

EXAMPLE

   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
      EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
      OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
         CRT 'OPEN FAILED'
         STOP
      END
   END
   READU V.REC FROM F.TEMP, 'REC1' LOCKED
      CRT 'Lock failure'
      STOP
   END ELSE NULL
   V.REC<-1> = 'A field'
   WRITE V.REC TO F.TEMP, 'REC1'

READV

READV statement allows a program to read a specific field from a record in a previously opened file into a variable.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READV variable1 FROM { variable2,} expression1, expression2 { SETTING setvar }  \
     { ON ERROR statements } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier into which the record will be read.

variable2 if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified, the default file is assumed.

expression1 should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

expression2 should evaluate to a positive integer. If the number is invalid or greater than the number of fields in the record, a NULL string will be assigned to variable1. If the number is 0, then the readv0 emulation setting controls the value returned in variable1. If a non-numeric argument is evaluated, a run time error will occur.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

If you wish to set a lock on a record, do so explicitly with the READU or READVU statement. To read a field from a previously opened file into a variable and take a read-only shared lock on the field, use READVL.

EXAMPLE

   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO f_temp THEN
      ret_error = ''
      CLEARFILE f_temp SETTING ret_error
      IF ret_error NE '' THEN
         CRT 'ERROR ' : ret_error
         STOP
      END
   END ELSE
      EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
      OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO f_temp ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP'
   END
   *
   out_record = 'Field 1' :@FM: 'Field 2' :@FM: 'Field 3'
   WRITE out_record TO f_temp, 'REC1'
   *
   READV second_field FROM f_temp, 'REC1', 2 ELSE
      CRT 'Read error'
      STOP
   END
   *
   CRT second_field           ;*  Field 2

READVU

READVU statement allows a program to read a specific field in a record in a previously opened file into a variable. It also respects record locking and locks the specified record for update.

COMMAND SYNTAX

READVU variable1 FROM {variable2,} expression1, expression2 { SETTING setvar }  \
       { ON ERROR statements } { LOCKED statements } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier into which the record will be read.

variable2 if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified then the default file is assumed.

expression1 should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

expression2 should evaluate to a positive integer number. If the number is invalid or greater than the number of fields in the record, then a NULL string will be assigned to variable1. If the number is 0, then the readv0 emulation setting controls the value returned in variable1. If a non-numeric argument is evaluated a run time error will occur.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the read fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

If ON ERROR is specified, the statements following the ON ERROR clause will be executed for any of the above Incremental File Errors except error 128.

NOTES

If the record could not be read because another process already had a lock on the record then one of two actions is taken. If the LOCKED clause was specified in the statement then the statements dependent on it are executed. If no LOCKED clause was specified then the statement blocks (hangs) until the other process releases the lock.

If the statement fails to read the record then any statements associated with the ELSE clause are executed. If the statement successfully reads the record then the statements associated with any THEN clause are executed. Either or both of the THEN and ELSE clauses must be specified with the statement.

The lock taken by the READVU statement will be released by any of the following events:

The same program with WRITE, WRITEV, MATWRITE or DELETE statements writes to the record.

The record lock is released explicitly using the RELEASE statement.

The program stops normally or abnormally.

When a file is OPENed to a local file variable in a subroutine then the file is closed when the subroutine RETURNS so all locks taken on that file are released, including locks taken in a calling program. Files that are opened to COMMON variables are not closed so the locks remain intact.

See also: WRITE, WRITEU, MATWRITE, MATWRITEU, RELEASE, and DELETE

EXAMPLE

OPEN "Customers" ELSE ABORT 201, "Customers"
OPEN "DICT Customers" TO DCusts ELSE
        ABORT 201, "DICT Customers"
END
LOOP
        READVU Rec FROM DCusts, "Xref",7 LOCKED
          CRT "Locked - retrying"
          SLEEP 1; CONTINUE ;* Restart LOOP
        END THEN
        READ DataRec FROM Rec ELSE
            ABORT 202, Rec
       END
       BREAK ;*leave the LOOP
   END ELSE
       ABORT 202, "Xref"
   END
REPEAT

RECORDLOCKED

RECORDLOCKED function is called to ascertain the status of a record lock.

COMMAND SYNTAX

RECORDLOCKED(filevar, recordkey)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

filevar is a file variable from a previously executed OPEN statement.

recordkey is an expression for the record id that will be checked.

NOTES

RECORDLOCKED returns an integer value to indicate the record lock status of the specified record id.

Code | Description
3 | Locked by this process by a FILELOCK
2 | Locked by this process by a READU
1 | Locked by this process by a READL
0 | Not locked
-1 | Locked by another process by a READL
-2 | Locked by another process by a READU
-3 | Locked by another process by a FILELOCK

If the return value is negative, then the SYSTEM(43) and STATUS function calls can be used to determine the port number of the program that holds the lock. If -1 is returned, more than 1 port could hold the lock and so the port number returned will be the first port number found.

EXAMPLE

Run this program from one session, wait for "RECORD LOCKED. PRESS ANY KEY TO WRITE" message, then run it in another session:

   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
      EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
      OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
         CRT 'OPEN FAILED'
         STOP
      END
   END
   READU V.REC FROM F.TEMP, 'REC1' LOCKED
      CRT 'Lock failure (' : RECORDLOCKED(F.TEMP, 'REC1') : ')'
      STOP
   END ELSE NULL
   PROMPT 'RECORD LOCKED. PRESS ANY KEY TO WRITE'
   INPUT DUMMY
   V.REC<-1> = 'A field'
   WRITE V.REC TO F.TEMP, 'REC1'

REMOVE

REMOVE will successively extract delimited strings from a dynamic array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

REMOVE variable FROM array SETTING setvar

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable is the variable, which is to receive the extracted string.

array is the dynamic array from which the string is to be extracted.

setvar is set by the system during the extraction to indicate the type of delimiter found:

Code | Description | Notes
0 | end of the array |
1 | xFF ASCII 255 |
2 | xFE ASCII 254 | Field marker
3 | xFD ASCII 253 | Value marker
4 | xFC ASCII 252 | Subvalue marker
5 | xFB ASCII 251 |
6 | xFA ASCII 250 |

NOTES

The first time the REMOVE statement is used with a particular array, it will extract the first delimited string it and set the special "remove pointer" to the start of the next string (if any). The next time REMOVE is used on the same array, the pointer will be used to retrieve the next string and so on. The array is not altered.

The variable named in the SETTING clause is used to record the type of delimiter that was found - so that you can tell whether the REMOVE statement extracted a field, a value or a subvalue for example. Delimiters are defined as characters between xF9 and xFF only. Once the end of the array has been reached, the string variable will not be updated and the SETTING clause will always return 0. You can reset the "remove pointer" by assigning the variable to itself - for example REC = REC.

EXAMPLE

   REC = "Field 1" :@FM: "Field 2" :@SM: " Sub-value" :@VM: "Value"
   REMOVE EXSTRING FROM REC SETTING V.STATUS  ; CRT V.STATUS         ;*  2
   REMOVE EXSTRING FROM REC SETTING V.STATUS  ; CRT V.STATUS         ;*  4
   REMOVE EXSTRING FROM REC SETTING V.STATUS  ; CRT V.STATUS         ;*  3
   REMOVE EXSTRING FROM REC SETTING V.STATUS  ; CRT V.STATUS         ;*  0
   REC = REC                   ;* reset "remove pointer"
   REMOVE EXSTRING FROM REC SETTING V.STATUS  ; CRT V.STATUS         ;*  2

REPLACE

REPLACE is an obsolete way to assign to dynamic arrays via a function.

COMMAND SYNTAX

REPLACE(var, expression1{, expression2{, expression3}}; expression4)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

var is the dynamic array that the REPLACE function will use to assign new values; remains unchanged.

expression1 specifies into which field assignment will be made and should evaluate to a numeric.

expression2 specifies into which value assignment is to be done and should evaluate to a numeric.

expression3 specifies into which sub-value assignment is to be done and should evaluate to a numeric.

expression4 can evaluate to any data type and is the actual data that will be assigned to the array.

NOTES

The function returns a copy of var with the specified replacement carried out. This value may be assigned to the original var in which case the jBC compiler will optimize the assignment.

EXAMPLE

   X = "jBASE" :@VM: "is" :@VM: "great" :@FM: '!'
   Y = REPLACE(X, 1, 2; 'is really')
   CRT FMT(X, 'MCP')                    ;*  jBASE]is]great^!
   CRT FMT(Y, 'MCP')                    ;*  jBASE]is really]great^!

SEEK

SEEK statement is used to move the file pointer by an offset specified in bytes, relative to the current position, the beginning of the file, or the end of the file.

COMMAND SYNTAX

SEEK file.variable [ , offset [ , relto] ] { THEN statements  \
   [ ELSE statements ] | ELSE statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

file.variable specifies a file previously opened for sequential access.

offset is the number of bytes before or after the reference position. A negative offset results in the pointer being moved before the position specified by relto. If offset is not specified, 0 is assumed.

The permissible values of relto and their meanings follow:

Value | Description
0 | Relative to the beginning of the file
1 | Relative to the current position
2 | Relative to the end of the file

If relto is not specified, 0 is assumed.

If the pointer is moved, the THEN statements are executed and the ELSE statements are ignored. If the THEN statements are not specified, program execution continues with the next statement.

If the file cannot be accessed or does not exist the ELSE statements are executed; any THEN statements are ignored.

If file.variable, offset, or relto evaluates to null, the SEEK statement fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

NOTES

In Windows-based systems, line endings in files are denoted by the character sequence RETURN + LINEFEED rather than the single LINEFEED used in UNIX files. The value of offset should take into account this extra byte on each line in Windows NT file systems.

If you use the OPENDEV statement to open a tape device for sequential processing, you can move the file pointer only to the beginning or the end of the data.

Seeking beyond the end of the file and then writing creates a gap, or hole, in the file. This hole occupies no physical space, and reads from this part of the file return as ASCII CHAR 0 (neither the number nor the character 0).

For more information about sequential file processing, See also: OPENSEQ, READSEQ, and WRITESEQ statements.

EXAMPLE

   V.DIR.OUT = '.'  ;   V.FILE.OUT = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ V.DIR.OUT, V.FILE.OUT TO F.FILE.OUT THEN
      WEOFSEQ F.FILE.OUT
   END ELSE
      CREATE F.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'File create error'  ;  STOP
   END
   WRITESEQ '1234567890ABCDEF' TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
      CRT 'Write error'
      STOP
   END
* go right after position 5 from the beginning
   SEEK F.FILE.OUT, 5, 0 ELSE CRT 'Seek error'  ;  STOP
   READSEQ V.STRING FROM F.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'Read error'  ;  STOP
   CRT V.STRING                 ;* 67890ABCDEF
* go beyond end of file and write something there
   SEEK F.FILE.OUT, 3, 2 ELSE CRT 'Seek error'  ;  STOP
   WRITESEQ 'VWXYZ' TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'Write error'  ;  STOP
   CLOSESEQ F.FILE.OUT
* read full file contents
   OSREAD V.ALL FROM V.FILE.OUT ELSE CRT 'Read error'  ;  STOP
   CRT FMT( FMT( OCONV(V.ALL, 'MX'), '2L'), 'MCP ')
* 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 30 41 42 43 44 45 46 FE 00 00 00 56 57 58 59 5A

SELECT

SELECT statement creates a select list of elements in a specified variable.

COMMAND SYNTAX

SELECT {variable1} { TO variable2 | listnum } { SETTING setvar }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 can be an OPENed file descriptor, in which case the record keys in the specified file will be selected, or an ordinary variable in which case each field in the variable will become a list element. variable1 may also be an existing list in which case the elements in the list will be selected.

If variable1 is not specified in the statement then it assumes the default file variable.

If variable2 is specified then the newly created list will be placed in the variable. Alternatively, specify a select list number in the range 0 to 10 with listnum. If neither variable2 nor listnum is specified then it assumes the default list variable.

If specifying the SETTING clause and the select fails, it sets setvar to one of the following values:

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

When constructing a list from record keys in a file, it does so by extracting only the first few keys, which when removed from the list obtains the next few keys and so on. Therefore, the creation of the list is not immediate. This means that the list could contain records, written to the file after starting the SELECT command.

Consider the situation where you open a file, SELECT it and then, because of the keys obtained, write new records to the same file. It would be easy to assume that these new keys would not show up in the list because you created the list before the new records existed. This is not the case. Any records written beyond the current position in the file will eventually show up in the list. In situations where this might cause a problem, or to ensure that you obtain a complete, qualified list of keys, you should use a slower external command like jQL SELECT or SSELECT and then READNEXT to parse the file.

If using a variable to hold the select list, then it should be unassigned or null before the SELECT. If it contains a number in the range 0 to 10 then it will use the corresponding select list number to hold the list, although you can still reference the list with the variable name. This "feature" is for compatibility with older platforms. See also example 3.

Lists can be selected as many times as required.

See also: the extensions for secondary indexes.

EXAMPLE 1

OPEN "Customers" ELSE ABORT 201, "Customers"
SELECT TO CustList1
SELECT TO CustList2

EXAMPLE 2

OPEN "Customers" TO CustFvar ELSE ABORT 201, "Customers"
SELECT CustFvar TO 2
Done = 0
LOOP
   READNEXT CustId FROM 2 ELSE Done = 1
UNTIL Done DO
   GOSUB ProcessCust
REPEAT

EXAMPLE 3

CLEAR
OPEN "Customers" TO CustFvar ELSE ABORT 201, "Customers"
OPEN "Products" TO ProdFvar ELSE ABORT 201, "Products"
SELECT CustFvar TO Listvar1
SELECT ProdFvar TO Listvar2

This example demonstrates a coding error. The CLEAR statement is used to initialize all variables to zero. Since Listvar1 has the value 0, select list number 0 is used to hold the list. However, the CLEAR statement also initializes Listvar2 to zero, so the second SELECT overwrites the first list.

SENTENCE

SENTENCE function allows a program to locate the command used to invoke it and the arguments it was given.

COMMAND SYNTAX

SENTENCE({expression})

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

If expression is specified it should evaluate to a positive integer value. A negative value will return a null string. A value of null will return the entire command line.

An integer value of expression will return a specific element of the command line with the command itself being returned by SENTENCE (0), the first parameter being returned by SENTENCE(1) and so on.

NOTES

It is assumed the command line arguments are space separated and when returning the entire command line they are returned as such. The SYSTEM(1000) function will return the command line attribute mark delimited.

EXAMPLES

   DIM Parm(4)
   ProgName = SENTENCE(0) ;* program is?
   FOR I = 1 TO 4
      Parm(I) = SENTENCE(I) ;* get parameters
   NEXT I

   this_prog = SENTENCE(0)    ;* name of this program
   phrase_part = 'to understand recursion '
   IF SENTENCE(1) EQ '-2' THEN              ;* first parameter
      CRT TRIM( SENTENCE(2), '"', 'B' ):    ;* 2nd parameter
      CRT phrase_part
   END ELSE
      CRT phrase_part:
      EXECUTE this_prog : ' -2 "you firstly need "'
   END

SORT

The SORT function sorts all elements of a dynamic array in ascending left-justified order.

COMMAND SYNTAX

SORT(expression)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

expression may evaluate to any data type but will only be useful if it evaluates to a dynamic array.

NOTES

The dynamic array can contain any number and combination of system delimiters.

The SORT function will return an attribute-delimited array of the sorted elements.

All system delimiters in expression will be converted to an attribute mark '0xFE' in the sorted result. For example, the following code

MyArray = 'GEORGE':@VM:'FRED':@AM:'JOHN':@SM:'ANDY'
CRT OCONV( SORT(MyArray), 'MCP')

will display:

    ANDY^FRED^GEORGE^JOHN

MyArray remains unchanged.

The SORT is achieved by the quick sort algorithm, which sorts in situ and is very fast.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When using the SORT function in International Mode, the function will use the currently configured locale to determine the rules by which each string is considered less than or greater than the other for sort purposes.

STATUS statement

STATUS statement is used to determine the status of an open file. It returns the file status as a dynamic array and assigns it to an array.

COMMAND SYNTAX

STATUS array FROM variable THEN statements ELSE statements | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

The STATUS statement returns the following values in the following attributes:

STATUS Statement Values

Attribute | Description
1 | Current position in the file Offset in bytes from
| beginning of file
2 | End of file reached 1 if EOF, 0 if not.
3 | Error accessing file 1 if error, 0 if not.
4 | Number of bytes available to read
5 | File mode Permissions (in octal) 6 File size in
| bytes.
7 | Number of hard links 0 if no links. Where applicable
| else 0
8 | O/S User ID. ID based on the user name and domain of
| the user a jBASE pseudo user.
9 | O/S Group ID.
10 | I-node number; Unique ID of file on file system
11 | Device on which i-node resides Number of device. The
| value is an internally calculated value on Windows
| NT.
12 | Device for special character or block Number of
| device.
13 | Time of last access in internal format
14 | Date of last access in internal format.
15 | Time of last modification in internal format
16 | Date of last modification in internal format.
17 | Time and date of last status change in internal
| format.
18 | Date of last status change in internal format.
19 | Number of bytes left in output queue (applicable to
| terminals only)
20 | { }
21 | jBASE File types j3, j4, jPLUS
22 | jBASE File types j3, j4, jPLUS
23 | jBASE File types j3, j4, jPLUS
24 | Part numbers of part files belonging to a
| distributed file multivalued list

variable specifies an open file. If variable evaluates to the null value, the STATUS statement fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

If the STATUS array is assigned to an array, the THEN statements are executed and the ELSE statements are ignored. If no THEN statements are present, program execution continues with the next statement. If the attempt to assign the array fails, the ELSE statements are executed; any THEN statements are ignored.

EXAMPLE

   IF NOT( GETENV('JEDIFILENAME_SYSTEM', FN.SYSTEM) ) THEN ABORT
   OPEN FN.SYSTEM TO F.SYSTEM ELSE NULL
   STATUS V.INFO.L FROM F.SYSTEM ELSE ABORT
   CRT V.INFO.L<5>       ;*  permissions in octal, e.g. 655
   CRT V.INFO.L<6>       ;*  file size in bytes
   CRT V.INFO.L<20>      ;*  full path to file
   CRT V.INFO.L<21>      ;*  file type, e.g. J4, JR, XMLDB2, SEQ

SUBROUTINE

SUBROUTINE statement is used at the start of any program that will be called externally by the CALL statement. It also declares any parameters to the compiler.

COMMAND SYNTAX

SUB{ROUTINE} Name {({ MAT } variable{,{ MAT } variable...})}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Name is the identifier by which the subroutine will be known to the compilation process. It should always be present as this name (not the source file name), will be used to call it by. However, if the name is left out, the compiler will name subroutine as the source file name (without suffixes). Default naming is not encouraged as it can cause problems if source files are renamed.

Each comma separated variable in the optional parenthesized list is used to identify parameters to the compiler. These variables will be assigned the values passed to the subroutine by a CALL statement.

NOTES

The SUBROUTINE statement must be the first code line in a subroutine.

All the variables declared using the COMMON statement will be inherited providing an equivalent common area is declared within the subroutine source file. The program will fail to compile if the number of common variables used in each common area exceeds the number defined in the equivalent area in the main program.

Subroutines can only be called via the jBC CALL statement.

PRECISION can be redefined but the new setting will not persist when the subroutine returns to the calling program.

The control will be returned to the CALLing program if the subroutine reaches the logical end of the program or a RETURN is executed with no outstanding GOSUB statement.

The control will not be returned to the calling program if a STOP or ABORT statement is executed.

See also: CALL, CATALOG Command, COMMON, RETURN.

EXAMPLES

SUBROUTINE DialUp(Number, MAT Results)
DIM Results(8)
....

TRANS

TRANS function returns the data value of a field, given the name of the file, the record key, the field number, and an action code.

COMMAND SYNTAX

TRANS([ DICT ] filename, key, field#, action.code)

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

DICT is the literal string to be placed before the file name in the event it is desired to open the dictionary portion of the file, rather than the data portion.

filename is a string containing the name of the file to be accessed. Note that it is the actual name of the file, and not a file unit variable. This function requires the file name, regardless of whether or not the file has been opened to a file unit variable.

key is an expression that evaluates to the record key, or item ID, of the record from which data is to be accessed.

field# is the field number to be retrieved from the record.

action.code indicates what should happen if the field is null, or the if record is not found. This is a literal. The valid codes are:

Code | Description
X | Returns a null string. This is the default action
V | Prints an error message.
C | Returns the value of key.

NOTES

If the field being accessed is a dynamic array, TRANS will return the array with the delimiter characters lowered by 1. For example, multivalue marks (ASCII-253) are returned as subvalue marks (ASCII-252), and subvalue marks are returned as text marks (ASCII-251).

If you supply -1 for field#, the entire record will be returned.

The TRANS function is the same as the XLATE function.

EXAMPLES

Retrieval of a simple field: Given a file called "VENDORS" containing a record with the record key of "12345" and which contains the value of "ABC Company" in field 1,

VENDOR.ID = "12345"
VENDOR.NAME = TRANS('VENDORS', VENDOR.ID, 1 , 'X')
CRT VENDOR.NAME

will display: ABC Company

Retrieval of an array: Suppose field 6 of the VENDORS file contains a multivalued list of purchase order numbers, such as:

    10011]10062]10079

use the TRANS function to retrieve it:

PO.LIST = TRANS('VENDORS', VENDOR.ID, 6, 'X')
CRT PO.LIST

will display: 1001100620079

Notice that the backslashes () were substituted for brackets (]), indicating that the delimiter is now CHAR(252).

Retrieval of an entire dictionary item: Given a dictionary item called "VENDOR.NAME" with the following content:

    001 A
    002 1
    003 Vendor Name
    004
    005
    006
    007
    008
    009 L
    010 30

these statements

DIC.ID = "VENDOR.NAME"
DIC.REC = TRANS('DICT VENDORS', DIC.ID, -1, 'C')
PRINT DIC.REC

will display

    A]1]Vendor Name]]]]]L]30

WRITEBLK

WRITEBLK statement writes a block of data to a file opened for sequential processing.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITEBLK expression ON | TO file.variable { THEN statements [ ELSE statements ] \
       | ELSE statements}

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Each WRITEBLK statement writes the value of expression starting at the current position in the file. The current position is incremented to beyond the last byte written. WRITEBLK does not add a new line at the end of the data.

file.variable specifies a file opened for sequential processing.

The value of expression is written to the file, and the THEN statements are executed. If no THEN statements are specified, program execution continues with the next statement. If the file is neither accessible or does not exist, it executes the ELSE statements; and ignores any THEN statements.

If either expression or file.variable evaluates to null, the WRITEBLK statement fails and the program enters the debugger with a run-time error message.

INTERNATIONAL MODE

When using the WRITEBLK statement in International Mode, care must be taken to ensure that the write variable is handled properly before the WRITEBLK statement. The WRITEBLK statement expects the output variable to be in "bytes", however when manipulating variables in International Mode character length rather than byte lengths are usually used and hence possible confusion or program malfunction can occur. If requiring byte count data the output variable can be converted from the UTF-8 byte sequence to 'binary/latin1' via the LATIN1 function.

It is not recommended that you use the READBLK/ WRITEBLK statements when executing in International Mode. You can obtain similar functionality via the READSEQ/ WRITESEQ statement, which can be used to read/write, characters a line at a time from a file.

NOTE

We have to explicitly create the output file if it doesnt exist (we didnt have to with WRITESEQ, for example, under prime emulation).

EXAMPLE

* Create a file with random name and write to it
   V.ID = ''
   FOR V.J = 1 TO 8
      V.RND = RND(26) + 65
      V.ID := CHAR(V.RND)        ;* A...Z
   NEXT V.J
   V.ID := '.txt'
   OPENSEQ '.', V.ID TO  F.FILE.OUT THEN
      WEOFSEQ F.FILE.OUT  ;* truncate the file
   END ELSE  ;* will have to create - WRITEBLK wouldn't do that
      CREATE F.FILE.OUT ELSE
         CRT 'FILE CREATION FAILURE'
         STOP
      END
   END
   V.BUFFER = 'LINE 1' : CHAR(10) : 'LINE 2' : CHAR(10) : 'LINE 3'
   WRITEBLK V.BUFFER TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
      CRT 'WRITE ERROR'
      STOP
   END
   CRT 'File ' : V.ID :  ' created'
   CLOSESEQ F.FILE.OUT
   STOP
END

WRITESEQ

WRITESEQ writes data to a file opened for sequential access.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITESEQ Expression { APPEND } ON | TO FileVar THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

Variable specifies the variable to contain next record from sequential file.

FileVar specifies the file descriptor of the file opened for sequential access.

Statements are conditional jBC statements

NOTES

Each WRITESEQ writes the data on a line of the sequentially opened file. Each data is suffixed with a new line character. After each WRITESEQ, the file pointer moves forward to the end of line. The WRITESEQF statement forces each data line to be flushed to the file when it is written. The APPEND option forces each WRITESEQ to advance to the end of the file before writing the next data line.

EXAMPLES

Create a file and write to it (overwriting contents each time):

   V.ID = 'report.txt'
   OPENSEQ '.', V.ID TO F.FILE.OUT THEN
      WEOFSEQ F.FILE.OUT  ;* truncate the file
   END
   WRITESEQ 'LINE 1' TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
      CRT 'WRITE ERROR'
      STOP
   END
   CRT 'File ' : V.ID :  ' written'
   CLOSESEQ F.FILE.OUT

Append data to file:

   V.DIR.OUT = '.'
   V.FILE.OUT = 'time.log'
   OPENSEQ V.DIR.OUT, V.FILE.OUT TO F.FILE.OUT THEN NULL
   WRITESEQ TIMEDATE() APPEND TO F.FILE.OUT ELSE
      CRT 'Write error'
      STOP
   END

If file was opened in read only mode, WRITESEQ will fail and statements defined after ELSE clause will be processed:

   IF NOT( GETENV('TAFC_HOME', tafc_home) ) THEN
      CRT 'TAFC_HOME not defined'
      STOP
   END
   //
   log_dir = tafc_home : '/tmp'
   log_file = 'jbase_error_trace'
   //
   OPENSEQ log_dir, log_file READONLY TO f_log THEN
   //
      FOR i = 1 TO 3   ;* read the first message
         READSEQ the_line FROM f_log ELSE BREAK
         CRT the_line
      NEXT i
   //
      WRITESEQ 'One more line' APPEND TO f_log ELSE
         CRT 'Write error'
         STOP
      END
   END ELSE
      CRT 'jbase_error_trace not found'
   END

Sample output:

     
    Trace message from pid 3588 port 237 at 'Mon May 28 14:02:41 2012'
        Port 1 (Pid 6184) has been inactive for 34317875 seconds, Port cleared
    Write error

WRITESEQF

WRITESEQF statement is used to write new lines to a file opened for sequential processing, and to ensure that data is physically written to disk (that is, not buffered) before the next statement in the program is executed.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITESEQF expression { ON | TO } file.variable [ ON ERROR statements ]  \
          { THEN statements [ ELSE statements ] | ELSE statements }

The sequential file must be open, and the end-of-file marker must be reached before you can write to the file. You can use the FILEINFO function to determine the number of the line about to be written.

Normally, when you write a record using the WRITESEQ statement, the record is moved to a buffer that is periodically written to disk. If a system failure occurs, you could lose all the updated records in the buffer. The WRITESEQF statement forces the buffer contents to be written to disk; the program does not execute the statement following the WRITESEQF statement until the buffer is successfully written to disk.

A WRITESEQF statement following several WRITESEQ statements ensures that all buffered records are written to disk. WRITESEQF is intended for logging applications and should not be used for general programming. It increases the disk I/O of your program and therefore degrades performance. file.variable specifies a file opened for sequential access.

The value of expression is written to the file as the next line, and the THEN statements are executed. If THEN statements are not specified, program execution continues with the next statement; if the specified file cannot be accessed or does not exist, the ELSE statements are executed; any THEN statements are ignored.

If expression or file.variable evaluates to the null value, the WRITESEQF statement fails and the program terminates with a run-time error message.

The ON ERROR Clause

The ON ERROR clause is optional in the WRITESEQF statement. Its syntax is the same as that of the ELSE clause. The ON ERROR clause lets you specify an alternative for program termination when a fatal error is encountered while the WRITESEQF statement is being processed.

WRITET

WRITET statement enables data to be written to a range of tape devices between 0-9.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITET variable { ON | TO expression } THEN | ELSE statements

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable is the variable that holds the data for writing to the tape device.

expression should evaluate to an integer value in the range 0-9 and specifies from which tape channel to read the data. If the ON clause is not specified the WRITET will assume channel 0.

If the WRITET fails then the statements associated with any ELSE clause will be executed. SYSTEM(0) will return the reason for the failure as follows:

Code | Description
1 | There is no media attached to the channel.
2 | End of media found.

NOTES

A "tape" does not refer to magnetic tape devices only but any device that has been described to TAFC. Writing device descriptors for TAFC is beyond the scope of this documentation.

If no tape device has been assigned to the specified channel the TAFC debugger is entered with an appropriate message.

Where possible the record size is not limited to a single tape block and the entire record will be written blocked to whatever block size has been allocated by the T-ATT command. However, certain devices do not allow TAFC to accomplish this (SCSI tape devices for instance).

EXAMPLE

LOOP
   WRITET TapeRec ON 5 ELSE
      Reason = SYSTEM(0)
      IF Reason = 2 THEN BREAK ;* done
      CRT "ERROR"  ;  STOP
   END
REPEAT

WRITEU

WRITEU statement allows a program to write a record into a previously opened file. An existing record lock will be preserved.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITEU variable1 ON | TO {variable2,} expression { SETTING setvar }  \
       { ON ERROR statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier holding the record to be written.

variable2, if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified then the default file is assumed.

The expression should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the write fails, setvar will be set to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

If the statement fails to write the record then any statements associated with the ON ERROR clause is executed.

The lock maintained by the WRITEU statement will be released by any of the following events:

The same program with WRITE, WRITEV or MATWRITE statements writes to the record.

The record lock is released explicitly using the RELEASE statement.

The program stops normally or abnormally.

See also: READU, MATREADU, RELEASE

EXAMPLE

   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
      EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
      OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO F.TEMP ELSE
         CRT 'OPEN FAILED'
         STOP
      END
   END
   READU V.REC FROM F.TEMP, 'REC1' LOCKED
      CRT 'Lock failure'
      STOP
   END ELSE NULL
   V.REC<-1> = 'A field'
   CRT RECORDLOCKED(F.TEMP, 'REC1')  ;* 2 - "Locked by this process by a READU"
   WRITEU V.REC TO F.TEMP, 'REC1'
   CRT RECORDLOCKED(F.TEMP, 'REC1')  ;* still 2
   RELEASE F.TEMP, 'REC1'
   CRT RECORDLOCKED(F.TEMP, 'REC1')  ;* 0 - not locked

WRITEV

WRITEV statement allows a program to write a specific field of a record in a previously opened file.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITEV variable1 ON | TO {variable2,} expression1, expression2  \
     { SETTING setvar } { ON ERROR statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier holding the record to be written.

variable2, if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified then it assumes the default file.

expression1 should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

expression2 should evaluate to a positive integer number. If the number is greater than the number of fields in the record, it will add null fields to variable1. If expression2 evaluates to a non-numeric argument, it will generate a run time error.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the write fails, it sets setvar to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

The WRITEV statement will cause the release of any lock held on the record by this program. If you wish to retain a lock on the record, do so explicitly with the WRITEVU statement.

EXAMPLE

   EXECUTE 'DELETE-FILE DATA F.TEMP'
   EXECUTE 'CREATE-FILE DATA F.TEMP 1 101 TYPE=J4'
   OPEN 'F.TEMP' TO f_temp ELSE ABORT 201, 'F.TEMP'
   new_rec = 'LINE 1' :@FM: 'LINE 2' :@FM: 'LINE 3'
   WRITE new_rec TO f_temp, 'REC1'
   WRITEV 'LINE 2v2' TO f_temp, 'REC1', 2 ON ERROR
      CRT 'WRITEV error'
      STOP
   END
   EXECUTE "I-DUMP F.TEMP 'REC1'"     ;* "REC1^LINE 1^LINE 2v2^LINE 3^"
   WRITEV 'LINE 7' TO f_temp, 'REC1', 7 ON ERROR
      CRT 'WRITEV error'
      STOP
   END
   EXECUTE "I-DUMP F.TEMP 'REC1'"     ;* "REC1^LINE 1^LINE 2v2^LINE 3^^^^LINE 7^"

WRITEVU

WRITEVU statement allows a program to write a specific field on a record in a previously opened file. An existing record lock will be preserved.

COMMAND SYNTAX

WRITEVU variable1 ON | TO {variable2,} expression1, expression2  \
      { SETTING setvar } { ON ERROR statements }

SYNTAX ELEMENTS

variable1 is the identifier holding the record to be written.

variable2, if specified, should be a jBC variable that has previously been opened to a file using the OPEN statement. If variable2 is not specified then the default file is assumed.

expression1 should evaluate to a valid record key for the file.

expression2 should evaluate to a positive integer number; if the number is greater than the number of fields in the record, null fields will be added to variable1. If expression2 evaluates to a non-numeric argument, a run time error will be generated.

If the SETTING clause is specified and the write fails, it sets setvar to one of the following values:

INCREMENTAL FILE ERRORS

Code | Description
128 | No such file or directory
4096 | Network error
24576 | Permission denied
32768 | Physical I/O error or unknown error

NOTES

If the statement fails to write the record, it executes any statements associated with the ON ERROR clause.

Any of the following events will release the lock taken by the WRITEVU statement:

The same program with WRITE, WRITEV or MATWRITE statements writes to the record.

By explicitly using the RELEASE statement, it releases the record lock.

The program stops normally or abnormally.

See also: MATWRITEU, RELEASE, WRITE, WRITEU.

EXAMPLE

OPEN "Customers" ELSE ABORT 201, "Customers"
OPEN "DICT Customers" TO DCusts ELSE
   ABORT 201, "DICT Customers"
END
WRITEVU Rec ON DCusts, 'Xref', 1 SETTING Err ON ERROR
   CRT "I/O Error[" :Err: "]"
   ABORT
END